Alrighty. Good evening, everybody. I
would like to call this regular session
of the city council meeting to order.
And I will call it to order at 6:02 p.m.
Can I get a roll call, please?
>> Council member Laura
>> here.
>> Council member Finn
>> Council member Martinez
>> here.
>> Mayor Pro Tim White
>> here. Mayor Foe
>> here. And um city attorney, can we get a
report out on close session, please?
>> Yes. The council met in closed session.
Item B1 was conference with legal
counsel regarding existing existing
litigation. That's the Rosa Maria Ruez
versus City of Bulmont matter. There was
no reportable action taken. Item B2,
conference with legal counsel regarding
potential initiation of litigation. Two
potential cases. No reportable action.
Item B3, conference with labor
negotiators. Uh, the A agency designated
representative Henry Garcia or his
design unrepresented potential employee.
City manager, no reportable action. Item
B4, public employee appointment,
employment
and the title of the position, city
manager, no reportable action taken.
Item B5, conference with legal counsel,
anticipated litigation, significant
exposure to litigation. one potential
case. There was no reportable action
taken.
>> All righty. Thank you. And if you could
please join me in an invocation by Mr.
Kent Spencer and followed by the pledge
of allegiance uh by Council Member
Martinez.
>> Good evening. Let's pray. Lord, I thank
you for the privilege to pray for this
council meeting tonight. Give each
member of the council and key
representatives wisdom in the decisions
that affect the people and the
businesses in Bowmont. May you bless all
that is said and done here tonight. We
ask all this things in your name, Jesus
Christ. Amen.
>> Please join me in the pledge of
allegiance.
>> Ready? Begin. I aliance to the flag of
the United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> All right. Uh do we have any adjustments
to the agenda?
>> Yes. Mayor and city council, we would
like to uh pull item G6 from the agenda
uh with no further action.
>> Okay, very good. We will be pulling item
G6
from the consent calendar.
[snorts]
>> Okay. Um do we know if there's any
public comments for item G6?
Thank you.
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line for item
G6? We have no callers at this time.
>> All right. Excellent. All right. And we
will begin our meeting with um
recognition for a special young man
today. So tonight we have the pleasure
of recognizing a very special young
member of our community has who has
earned a truly remarkable opportunity.
So Alonszo, are you here with us today?
All right. I see him sitting over there.
Alonzo is joining us this evening as he
was recently invited to join the Real
Madrid Soccer Club. That's exciting.
That's a I think a local club here,
isn't it?
>> No, it's a um club in Spain. It's the
best club um worldwide.
>> Oh, awesome. So, for those of you who
follow soccer, you know this is an
extraordinary achievement and a rare
opportunity for a player of any age. At
just nine years old, Alonzo has already
shown that his dedication, discipline,
and love for the sport are setting him
apart as a truly talented young athlete.
We are also honored tonight to have
Alonzo's mother, Anna, here with us
along with his coach, Ivan, and
representatives from his school. Um, can
we have Alonzo and um his mom and his
coach come up to the podium, please?
Alrighty. Well, Alonzo, you have worked
incredibly hard to get here and the city
of Bumont is very proud to have you
representing our community on the field
field. We will be cheering you on every
single step of the way. So, we have a
little certificate for you and the
certificate says in certificate of rec
recognition, excuse me, Bumont Youth
Real Madrid Foundation, Alonzo Guen for
the athletic achievements of being
selected to train with the Real Madrid
Soccer Club in Madrid, Spain. Alonzo was
one of 22 soccer players chosen by Real
Madrid from a nationwide group. The city
of Bumont is pleased to honor you and
your achievements.
Yay. [applause]
Come on up here. [applause]
All
>> [applause]
>> right. Ready? One, two, three.
>> All right. One, one more. One, two,
three.
Let's
[applause]
take one one more.
>> Let's do one more real quick with mom.
Sorry.
>> Yes.
All right,
there we are. Ready? One, two, three.
Good.
[applause]
>> Yes. As a soccer player myself, I am and
my kiddo, I am proud of you. That's a
lot of hard work and keep up the
dedication. It can take you far. The
things you learn in sports can really
help you in life. All right. Um, we have
one more recognition uh as well, and
this is recognition of our finance
director, Jennifer Ustation. So,
Jennifer joined the city of Bulma in
2017 as a senior accountant. In 2021,
she briefly served as interim finance
director before being selected for the
permanent position in which she
currently holds. Jennifer has been a
valuable contributor to the city of
Bowmont's growth and success. And while
we will greatly miss her leadership, we
wish her continued success in your next
endeavor. Jennifer, [snorts] we really
appreciate all that you've done. You've
brought um significant knowledge, the
GFOA awards, um and truly financial
transparency.
um to a city that needed that. Um and so
we really appreciate all of the work
that you have done for us and we really
wish you the best. You are dynamite. Um
and I know that wherever you go, you
will lead with grace and you will shine.
So congratulations.
>> Anybody else on the council want to say
anything?
>> On top of everything else that you've
done for the city, you've improved our
reputation significantly and we
appreciate that.
And Jennifer, thank you for making um
finance something that everyone could
understand. I appreciate all your
efforts in that regard.
>> Made our city proud and we're going to
miss you. So, good luck in your future.
>> Jennifer, you did a wonderful job. Um
built a good team and and having served
on the finance and audit committee, um I
certainly learned a lot and it's and
you've been a good resource and and we
wish you the best in in your next
endeavor. We're going to miss you.
>> Congratulations. Good luck.
>> [applause]
>> Yeah,
I do.
>> I I I wrote something so I I have to say
something and I'm going try to get
through this without crying anymore.
[laughter] So, I thank you, mayor and
council. It has truly been an honor to
serve the city of Bumont. I started here
in 2017 as a senior accountant and I'm
incredibly grateful for the opportunity
to grow into the role of finance
director. I'm proud of the work we've
accomplished together. Strengthening
financial policies, building sustainable
reserves, modernizing systems, and
creating long-term forecasting tools
that support informed decision-making.
But none of that happens because of one
person. It happens because of strong
leadership from this council and a
dedicated finance team that works hard
every day behind the scenes. I've been
fortunate to work alongside people who
genuinely care about this community.
>> [snorts]
>> So, as I move on to my next chapter, I
leave knowing the city has the tools,
policies, and framework in place to
navigate whatever the future may bring.
So, thank you for the opportunity to
serve this community.
>> Thank you. [applause]
>> One more photo.
>> [laughter]
>> All right. Ready? One, two, three.
>> Good.
What else?
>> There you go.
>> That'll work. That'll work. Scoot over a
little bit so they can squeeze in too.
Yeah, right there. Perfect. And you guys
are all good.
>> Do you want me to get p up top? There we
go.
>> All right. Ready? One, two, three.
And one more just for good measure.
Ready? One, two, three.
>> Good.
[applause]
All right, we will be moving on.
Hold on one second.
All right, we will be moving on to our
public comment period for items that are
not on the agenda. Any one person may
address the city council on any matter
not on this agenda. If you wish to
speak, please fill out a public comment
form provided at the back table and give
it to the city clerk. There's a
threeminut time limit on public
comments. There's no sharing or passing
of time to another person. State law
prohibits the city council from
discussing or taking actions brought up
by your comments. Um Nicole, do we have
any public comment? I have no written
requests. Simone, do we have any callers
on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All righty, then we will be moving to
consent calendar. Um, are there any
items to be pulled for discussion?
Okay, seeing none, are there any public
comments
on consent?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any new callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All right. Well, prior to um making a
motion or taking a motion, I would just
like to make a comment on item G7. Um I
just really wanted to say thank you for
once again bringing this forward as
Highland Springs traffic and continuing
uh to improve traffic along Highland
Springs has been a priority for the
council. So, I appreciate uh seeing an
item on here for um us to continue that
with the implementation of the AI
traffic signals. So, thank you. And I
will entertain a motion.
>> Mayor, I'll make a motion to approve
consent calendar items G1 through G5 and
G7 through G9.
>> I'll second.
>> All right. Can I get a roll call?
>> Council member Laura?
>> Yes.
>> Council member Finn?
>> Council member Martinez?
>> Yes. Mayor Promay.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Foy,
>> yes.
Right, that takes us to item eight,
youth council report. Do we have a youth
council report tonight?
>> Yes, we do.
>> Great. Come on up, ladies.
So, we
>> Oh,
>> okay.
Uh we had a meeting on February 10th and
we got to meet our lovely mayor and we
got to ask her questions all about uh
why she became mayor, what are her
plans, what she's hoping on
accomplishing during her time and we got
to learn a lot more about just why she
why she is mayor and more about her in
general. We got to learn about her
passions and what drives her to continue
working and it was great.
Wonderful. Thank you guys. It was an
absolute honor to be with you guys. You
truly surprised me with your questions
that you guys asked. They stumped me at
times. Like, oh my gosh, I wouldn't have
even thought to to ask that question.
So, just a word of encouragement as
always to you guys. Like we talked
about, you know, continue to focus on
the community, continue to provide
services and and get involved. and I'm
really proud of all the work that you
guys are doing um under the direction of
council member Martinez. It's really
awesome to see you guys push forward.
You guys have a very bright future.
>> Thank you.
>> So, thank you.
>> All right, we will move to our public
hearings. Um item I
uh the third amendment to the fiscal
year 2026 through 2030 capital
improvement plan. And we will have our
first staff report by Matthew Mendoza.
And yeah,
>> good evening, Mayor and Council. Just
give me one second to get a slide up.
All right, we can see it.
>> Good evening, mayor and council. Again,
sorry. Um before you today is the
proposed third amendment to the city's
5-year capital improvement plan from
fiscal years 2026 through 2030. Staff is
proposing to amend the CIP by adding one
new project, revising five project
budgets, and closing three projects. Uh
starting with the new project request
F2604.
Uh this project is intended to provide
funding for the rehabilitation of
building E uh to serve as an interim
animal shelter um with the potential for
future growth. Um while this item was
brought forth for a discussion on
February 3rd, um this CIP amendment is
necessary to formally establish and fund
the project. Um secondly, uh staff is
requesting a budget change for CIP 2604,
which is for the traffic signal
installation at Second Street in
Pennsylvania.
Um these funds uh will be transferred
from a recently completed uh CIP uh CIP
R34. Um so there is no fiscal impact to
the general fund.
Nextly, uh staff is requesting a budget
change for uh the bicycle and pedestrian
path. Uh this is associated with the
adopted city's uh bike and p pedestrian
connectivity plan master plan. Uh the
majority of these funds come from a
recently approved SB821 grant agreement
um with RCTC. uh and the remaining
portion will be uh coming from CIP R36
which was also recently completed.
In addition, uh staff is requesting a
budget change for uh R25-14,
which is the uh Petrero [clears throat]
bike lane upgrade. Uh this project will
be funded through the remainder of the
funds in CIP R36
um that were not allocated to the
previous uh master plan implementation.
Um
next we have a amendment to a grant
award uh for the transit yard. Um this
is the Carl Moyer grant uh for the CNG
station at the new transit yard. Um due
to some
uh due to some uh
updated projections um there is no
longer um
as high of an output projected and part
of the grant was calculated based on uh
what our expected annual usage would be.
So with our transit fleet converting to
CNG but then with zero mission
transition the projected sales are going
down and so the scale of the station
will be decreasing. Um so this is uh to
memorialize that funding change.
And lastly, um staff is requesting to
close out CIP R2505 for the 8th Street
uh sidewalk feasibility. Um this project
was recently completed. Uh and the
remaining balance can be transferred
back to the city's diff balance uh to be
used for a future project.
And with that uh that concludes my
presentation and I would like to open up
uh the conversation for any questions.
All righty. Great. Thank you, Mr.
Mendoza. I will open up this public
hearing at 6:23.
And Nicole, do we have any public
comments?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All right, then I will close the public
hearing at 6:23 and open it up for
further council discussion.
Council member Martinez.
>> Yeah, thank you, Mayor. Just a quick
question on the R2514.
Um, it says that we're reallocating
from R36
uh back to 2514. Correct? Because we
that one's complete. So, we're putting
it back to Well, we're putting it 2514.
My question is, so it shows general
fund. So, is that something we typically
do? We move it over to general fund and
then move it over to the CIP that we're
we plan to reallocate it to.
Typically, uh we would bring it forth
during the CIP amendment if we plan to
use it towards other projects. Uh if
not, then it would go straight to the
CIP general fund balance.
>> Okay. So, it's going to be then going to
the um bike lane project fund. So,
that's going to increase it um court to
looks like 23981.
Correct. Um, and do we have a plan for
that money now or is it just in that
account until we have further projects?
>> Uh, since that project is complete, uh,
there's there's no need for that funds
in the current project it's in. Um,
>> but for the pro I'm asking. So,
>> sorry. For the new project.
>> Yeah. So, for the Peturo project, we're
loading it with 239. Do we have plans
for that money or is it
>> Yes, we do. I'll address that one,
Matthew, if you're all right with that.
>> Yeah. So, council will see the the
Petero bike lane uh improvement very
quickly. We we had a field walk out
there. We think there's a a a great
opportunity to do some really neat
enhancements along in between First and
Pennsylvania Avenue. The extra cost, the
extra cash or or uh money, excuse me,
will allow us to um really enhance it a
little bit more than some striping.
>> Okay. and and
when you reallocate and you prioritize.
So, we moved it from the citywide uh
street since we're complete with that
project. We're moving it over here to
this one with the Peturo bike. How do
you prioritize from all the different
projects we have that it's going into
that one? I mean, how did you decide to
put that much into that one? Is it
>> Sure. It's based on [clears throat]
it's based on need and amount. Uh we for
that project in particular, it's kind of
been lagging because we knew that the I
believe it was $50,000 originally wasn't
sufficient to to carry it all the way.
So we're kind of waiting for additional
funds to come available. uh these did
they're not substantial enough to really
impact like the grade separation or a
paturero project. However, council is
free to direct staff to uh apply it
somewhere else. Well, and that's that's
the only reason I ask is just because,
you know, as we had talked in the past
about funding um shortfalls and so
forth, you know, I have this vision of
anytime we can save money instead of,
you know, going forward with the
possible project, let's see, is there
anywhere we can infill, you know,
without cutting projects because I know
council member White you had mentioned,
you know, we won't want to stop going
forward with projects and I agree with
that. I was just wondering where the
priority came from as if you just
is there any other way you can look and
see where else we can put not that it's
not deserved. I'm just questioning that
process. That's all I'm doing. So, um
I'll go ahead and and I don't have a
problem with it being there, but what I
do have a concern with is going in the
future some coming up with shortfalls
somewhere and then saying, "Well, we had
money here, but we used it over here
instead." So, if you can kind of use
your crystal ball and predict, you know,
if we're not going to have any
shortfalls right here immediately, then
I'm okay with moving that money there.
If you guys think that that's the, you
know, proper place to put it. I don't
want to micromanage. So, you know, I
agree with your professional opinion,
but that's that's the premise I always
put out. Just remember that as things
come up, I don't want to come back and
have, oh, we could have used that to
something somewhere else. You know,
that's all. So, just a word of caution
for that.
Thank you, mayor.
>> Anyone else? All right. With that, then
I'll entertain a motion. [snorts]
>> Mayor, did we open and close the public
hearing?
>> Yes. Okay. Apologies. All right. So,
I'll move that we wave the full reading
and adopt by title only a resolution of
the city council of the city of Bowmont
amending the 5-year capital improvement
plan for fiscal year 2026 through 2020.
I'll second.
>> I get a roll call, please.
>> Council member Laura,
>> yes.
>> Council member Finn,
>> Council member Martinez,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Pro Tim White,
>> Mayor Voit,
>> yes.
>> All righty, that takes us to action
items. Item J1, approval of professional
services agreement with Spicer
Consulting Group for fiscal impact model
development and fiscal impact analysis
review services. And Miss Station, one
of your last ones,
>> one of them. [laughter]
I'm not gone quite yet.
So, tonight I'm requesting approval
professional services agreement with
Spicer Consulting Group to develop a
city-owned fiscal impact model and
provide fiscal impact review services.
So, as development activity comes
through the process, it's critical that
the city evaluate projects using
consistent assumptions and methodologies
to protect the long-term sustainability
of the general fund. Um, historically
staff have relied on applicant prepared
studies and consultant reviews on a
projectby-p project basis. While
effective, that approach does not
provide a standardized framework owned
and controlled by the city. So, this
agreement would allow us to establish a
uniform fiscal impact model that applies
consistent revenue and cost assumptions
line with adopted budget and fiscal
policies, distinguishes between fixed
and variable service costs, identifies
service thresholds that may require
additional staffing or capital
investment, um, and is delivered in an
edible format under city control. So,
this model will serve as the baseline
tool for eval evaluating all future
development projects and reviewing
applicant prepared analysis. In
addition, Spicer will use the city's
[clears throat] model to conduct project
specific fiscal reviews as needed to
ensure consistency with our policies and
assumptions. Um, staff recommends Spicer
based on their familiarity with the
city's general fund structure and prior
fiscal analysis work. Um, staff also
reached out to two other firms who
indicated that they could not provide
these services um or recommended our
current CFD administrator for this
scope. So, the fiscal impact model will
cost 12,500 funded from contingency.
Project specific reviews will range from
2500 to 12,000 depending on complexity
and are anticipated to be funded through
development review fees. The total
agreement is not to exceed 40,000. Uh
and staff recommends um approval. So I'm
happy to answer any questions you have
and Shane Spicer is also in the audience
for any questions.
>> Great. Thank you. Do we have any public
comments for this item?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> Okay. Seeing none of then I will open up
to council discussion.
>> Is there a condition that Miss Station
follows this project through?
>> Should [laughter] be. I I agree.
>> I I just want to say thank you for doing
the due diligence to go out and see if
there was anybody else um uh for the
project. And as we hear it sounds like
we have the person for the job. So, I
will go ahead and uh make a motion to
approve a new professional services
agreement with Spicer Consulting Group
and an amount not to exceed 40,000 to
provide fiscal impact model development
and fiscal impact analysis review
services.
>> I'll second.
>> Can I get a roll call, please?
>> Council member Laura,
>> yes.
>> Council member Finn,
>> Council member Martinez,
>> yes. C Mayor Prom White,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Voit,
>> All right. And that takes us to our
neighborhood traffic program. Um, and we
will have [snorts]
an
staff report by Robert Bestl.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Thank you, Mayor.
>> It, if I can get my screen shown.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. So, the city of Bulmont's
neighborhood traffic management plan,
uh, NTMP, is designed to address traffic
safety concerns in residential
neighborhoods such as speeding,
increased traffic, uh, volumes, and
changing land use. The program uses a
balanced datadriven approach that
prioritizes neighborhood livability,
public safety, and efficient uh,
mobility. Solutions are developed
through collaboration among residents,
the public works department, law
enforcement, schools, traffic
engineering professionals, and other
city stakeholders.
Uh, all measures follow state law and
standards, including the California
code, CVC,
California Vehicle Code, excuse me, CVC,
and the California Manual on Uniform
Traffic Control Devices, also known as
MUTCD.
The NTMP, the neighborhood traffic
management program,
includes five key steps
which is initiated first with the
request or petition is generally
initiated by residents,
uh, other staff members or even council
members.
Residents submit their concerns or
petitions to to public works online.
After we receive it, we initiate phase
two, which is the evaluation. City staff
conducts traffic studies, field reviews,
and data analysis.
That moves to the third phase, which is
a response. Findings and potential
solutions are shared with the resident.
And then lastly, not lastly, excuse me,
uh second to last, implementation.
>> Excuse me, Robert. If you're doing
slides, we're not seeing any changes.
>> Yeah, I'm not doing I'm sorry.
>> Okay. All right. Just making sure. We're
missing out.
>> So boring.
>> We're missing out on the [laughter]
slides.
>> Yeah, I apologize.
[laughter]
>> So implementation approved measures are
installed. Uh timelines vary by measure.
And then finally, lastly, review post
installation monitoring ensures
effectiveness.
>> Hey.
>> Yeah. Sorry about that. That was
[laughter] way too long for one [snorts]
[clears throat] one slide. All right.
[laughter]
Uh, so purpose and why this matters.
This formalizes the city's approach to
neighborhood traffic safety concerns.
It's transparent
and has a consistent framework.
It complies with the state law and
engineering standards.
uh residents frequently request traffic
calming measures which is why this
really is uh important and why it
matters. In this last year we received
33 requests. Uh half of those about 16
were requests for stop signs. about five
of them were for speed humps or speed
bumps uh in their request and then a a
mix of traffic signals, curb painting uh
and some specialties.
Uh and lastly,
this
this program is comparable with other
cities like HIT, Riverside, Redlands,
Anaheim, and several others.
>> [clears throat]
>> Key benefits
as mentioned before it it's a citywide
consistency.
It ensures compliance with the
California vehicle code and the MUTCD.
It's datadriven decisions. It's
transparent and fair. And it's bal it
balances livability and emergency
access.
All right. So, traffic calming measures.
Just a quick note,
the the items listed here are the ones
that we routinely implement. As the city
develops new measures and adopts um
emerging measures from other cities and
other uh agencies, we'll add this into
the the document. A good example of a a
measure that's not included is traffic
striping.
Similar to when you get off the uh SR60
onto Sixth Street. You'll notice that
there's lines on either side. That is a
visual uh measure to help
reduce speeds.
I didn't slow down, so I'm not not sure
of its effectiveness, but
uh certainly potential to be added into
the uh
the document. So the ones that we
routinely implement are enforcement that
that's exclusively through PD
uh traffic signs and pavement markings.
That would be speed limits. Uh
additional signage uh no truck routes
would be one. stop signs, traffic
signals, and then lastly, speed humps.
Speed humps is in addition to this
document.
Um
I I don't think I mentioned this
earlier, but uh council has heard a
verbal
um presentation of this document about
three years ago. It was done under the
city manager's
report, so it wasn't a formal document.
We have since formalized it, and that's
what you're receiving today.
All right. So, let's get into speed
humps. I think we're all familiar with
stop signs
and traffic signals, but the
we're not, as of [clears throat] yet,
the city has not adopted a speed hump
policy, which is why this document is
really being brought forth. So, what are
speed humps? Speed humps are raised
pavement features designed to slow
vehicles on residential streets while
maintaining reasonable driver comfort.
They differ from speed bumps because
they provide gradual deflection,
reducing discomfort and vehicle damage.
A speed bump is typically found in a
commercial parking lot. It's very
abrupt. No one really enjoys those. A
speed hump is an engineering engineered
measure um really designed for the speed
at which you want to control traffic at.
The purpose is it it's intended to
reduce vehicle speeds and improve
neighborhood safety commonly used in
residential areas where speeding is a
concern.
In this document, the policy and
approval process
uh requires a petition. So it starts
with a a citizen petition where a
particular resident or a group
[clears throat] would need to secure 70%
of the affected households uh within
that that street.
The city would review uh traffic studies
and emergency service coordination. We
would engage fire and PD to make sure
that the site uh warrants
speed humps, but also that there are no
objections to the installation of a
speed hump in that location.
And then it would require city council
approval via a public hearing before
installation.
The timeline typically 6 months to two
years from request to installation. The
elig eligibility is what's shown on your
screen.
It has to be a residential uh street,
one lane in each direction. Has to be a
quarter mile or longer. Uh with a speed
limit of 25 miles per hour or less. The
street width has to not exceed 40 ft.
And the grade has to be 8% or less. And
it lastly, it cannot be a primary
emergency or transit route.
Some of the considerations and drawbacks
of speed humps is it does slow traffic
and improve safety for pedestrians and
cyclists. However, it does increase
noise from breaking and acceleration.
Drivers may speed between humps. uh
longer travel times for residents in
emergency vehicles and increased vehicle
emu emissions.
Oh, I was supposed to take that out.
[laughter]
Sorry.
>> Yeah, for sure.
So the the action today is to uh adopt
this policy
as I had mentioned earlier the city has
been implementing all of the other
criteria except for the speed humps
within the last year and we've been very
effective about it. Our response time is
within two weeks to notify the the um
the resident and then implementation
time after that really depends on our
ability to collect data and then also
the uh actual
measure implemented. So a traffic signal
can take up to two years. A stop sign
can take up to a week to to six months.
So with that, I'll open it up to any
questions.
All right. Thank you, Mr. Vestal. Do we
have any public comments for this item?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All right, then I will open it up to
council discussion.
I can You want to start us off? You want
me to?
>> I just wanted Yeah, if you would.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> I just wanted to give them a comment
that I appreciate the speed hump in
there. When I was mayor, it was one of
the frequent things that I was called on
about speed humps and we really didn't
have a way to talk it out with the
residents about why or why they would be
or wouldn't be a good idea, you know.
So, I like the way that the procedure
set out and it is consistent and would
follow this for everyone and and go with
whether the criteria matches or not. So,
I appreciate that. But I think this is
going to really help um with those
residents that un don't understand or
perhaps want it but they don't they have
to now get their neighbors involved
within the neighborhood. So I appreciate
that. So that was all I wanted to
mention.
>> Yeah. Thank you. And um I have a I have
a question regarding that. Um with
regards to the 70% of households in the
area, is that specific to the speed
humps or any of these uh changes that
are requested? Yeah, it is specific to
the speed humble only.
>> Okay, very good. And then um just a a
question and maybe a discussion for my
other council members up here. I if we
have designated that um fire I think
where you can paint the curb colors. We
have designated that authority to the
public works director. Um, is there an
appetite to continue to direct this
decision to the public works director
versus bringing it forward as a council
discussion if it meets all the criteria?
I mean, it seems very data driven and
kind of approached. I I don't know if
there's an appetite for that, but that
was something that I was I was thinking
about. If they met all the requirements,
it's going to be the recommendation from
the um director of public works, then
does it need to have a further level of
bureaucracy from us? I I don't know the
answer, but just a a thought um that
maybe we could walk through.
>> Um
>> Mayor, yeah,
>> may I? Thanks. Um I think it's a good
question. U Robert, we have some other
cities that have put those in. Do you
know if they have gone to council for
all those decisions?
Some do, some don't. The ones that do um
have emphasized the ability to make it a
public notice is really the emphasis,
not necessarily the council. um
approval.
>> Okay. Gotcha. Perhaps maybe a good
compromise would be that it'd be, you
know, come forward as a consent, you
know, item that it's there. It's it's
it's
>> noticed
>> noticed and so forth and then the
council if they need to comment on it or
or so forth and then we could we could
pull it for discussion if it was needed,
if it was maybe somebody there's
opposition to it outside of maybe the
support, you know, that gives the the
the public opportunity to come and and
voice their opinion. Yeah, I think
that's a good perspective. Council
member uh excuse me, Mayor Pro Tim
White,
>> um just uh the first restriping of the
road out here, did that come to council
>> uh on Sixth Street?
>> Yeah,
>> it did not.
>> Yeah, I think we should have this come
to council.
>> Okay. Council member Lara.
>> Yeah, you did mention that once you have
finished your review, it does come to
council for approval, correct? or no,
>> for the speed hump only.
>> Okay.
So, yeah, for speed hump only. I'm okay
with that. I I do appreciate the fact
that you've got this in a policy now
that has a specific flow to it.
Obviously, um it's data driven, Mr.
Engineer. Um appreciate that. Um have
you ever considered in lie of speed
humps? I know that some cities have done
um I just call them larger size
truncated domes um similar to they're
similar to like the ADA ones only
they're they're bigger and they're I
think they also work as a traffic
calming and aggravating and agitating as
well.
>> Yes. So that that is definitely a
possibility. I I think
public works should explore that
further.
>> Okay. H. However, just on on the
surface, they are quite noisy and they
require continual maintenance. They they
pop up, get dislodged frequently.
>> Okay. Yeah. No, then I'm I'm good with
the humps. If the noise, I guess, would
be an issue as well if you don't I
hadn't thought of that. Thank you very
much, Mr. Vestto. I appreciate that.
Good job.
>> All right. Well, if nothing further, do
we have
uh a motion or any other discussion?
Mayor, I'll move that we adopt I move
that we adopt the neighborhood traffic
management plan.
>> I'll second.
>> Right. Can I get a roll call?
>> Council member Laura?
>> Yes.
>> Council member Finn?
>> Council member Martinez?
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Proim White?
>> Mayor Voy?
>> Yes.
>> All right. That takes us to item J3, the
Cherry Festival 2026 relocation
analysis.
And the uh staff report is going to be
by Mr. Mr. Romo.
>> Yes. Thank you, mayor, members of the
city council. So, the idea today is to
give you a cost breakdown for the
potential relocation of the cherry
festival to the city-owned 30acre site
over on Cougar and Bowmont Avenue. Uh on
February 3rd, uh you requested that
staff look at what these costs would
entail uh and return tonight with a cost
breakdown. uh the analysis that we have
presented to you tonight. It identifies
the anticipated cost categories that are
associated with the cherry festival um
at this proposed site but also
distinguishes between the city and the
foundation's cost. The cherries of the
past foundation who by the way we do
have uh staff members here and board
member correct? Yes. So we are
identifying with the exception of
entertainment, community engagement and
food beer categories uh estimates that
are primarily based on the 2025 event
costs. And given um our timeline here,
these are planning level estimates. We
have not yet taken the site plan to the
city's DRC for review. Uh so in looking
at what we broke down, we first looked
at the planning level city costs uh to
be able to prepare this site for the
temporary event. So again, we're looking
at what we look would look at uh Noble
Creek, which would be the full service
traffic control, uh the perimeter
fencing that would be needed. Keeping in
mind that after putting this report
together, we did talk to the foundation
about the foundation taking on the
responsibility of the fencing. So you'll
see in the cost breakdown that the
foundation has an estimate for perimeter
and interior fencing, temporary fencing
of a little under $15,000.
So if they were to take on that
responsibility, this 78,000 would go
away. So the city would no longer be
responsible for that. Uh we're also
looking at the temporary lighting for
the parking lot and the event area. Um
the temporary water service and we have
talked to our water uh agency about
this. There's a possibility for
sponsorship there but we don't know just
yet. Uh portable restrooms, handwashing
stations, event security uh again
everything that we anticipate for a
vacant site. contracted wheat abatement,
but also keeping in mind that that is a
possible sponsorship opportunity. So
that might not have to be city costs. It
could be a sponsorship cost. Uh and also
there is a cost savings in the sense
that we're already anticipating the weed
payment for that site because it's
city-owned and we have to do it prior to
the Fourth of July event. So again,
that's a cost that not necessarily would
take place because we're already doing
it overtime for police services,
supplemental fire services, uh shuttle
services to and from the event. Uh
public works staff for the event and
community services staff as well. Um
temporary shade structures, again that
could also be responsibility of the
foundation.
uh special event insurance
system for collecting parking fees if
the city decided to charge fees. And
again, we have a total of about 1320
parking spaces possible at this
facility. Um the idea of also having
just VIP parking as part of the
pre-sales could be put in there. That
means uh maybe we could have a hundred
VIP parking spaces dedicated uh for
anyone that wants to come in and you
know be parked right in the front so
they can enter the event quickly. So the
total cost with a contingency of 10%
we're talking about $412,766.
Now in uh 2025 the city had a total
event cost of about $260,000.
When we look at the cherries of the past
foundation costs,
they would be saving the first item that
you see there, the rental of the
facility, or they could be providing
that to the city to offset your costs.
So again, that's 50,000 that they would
have paid for the Noble Creek rental.
Um, we look at tables, chairs, food
court, and stage areas, which they would
also be doing. Uh either way, also event
security, uh the water truck and
sanitation services. And so looking at
all these uh and keeping in mind too, we
put this in here, the entertainment has
been fully sponsored, but we're pending
official statement. So last year the
city provided $100,000 as a donation.
This year it's fully paid for. So the
city has the opportunity to provide that
for something else, but it wouldn't have
to go to the entertainment anymore. So
all in all, the foundation costs are
$264,819.
Currently, the Cher's Foundation has a
total uh budget of $142,500,
but they're here to elaborate on that,
too. So we're anticipating a gap of
122,000. But again, keeping in mind what
I just told you about some of the things
that could be sponsored that could go
down to as low as $70,000.
So, additional considerations for this
site, there's a middle school located
across Cougar. Uh, but to reduce any
conflicts with school operations,
festival activities on Thursday and
Friday are planned after 5:00 p.m. So,
there wouldn't be any conflict with the
school. Uh and the scheduling approach
is intended to minimize noise,
pedestrian activity, anything that's
happening to Long Cougar. Preliminary
public safety review. Now, both police
and fire, we have talked to our chiefs
and our staff. Uh they don't see any
issue with this site. Um no uh
additional concerns that would say these
are unsurmountable. Uh however, there
will be additional review as part of the
DRC process. Uh so the site plans are
being refined and the event details as
well will be finalized as part of that
DRC review process. The other thing to
consider is weather and site conditions.
As you know with an event taking place
on a 30 acre vacant site um there's
always risk uh risks that are related to
weather conditions. If there's ponding
for instance on the site, if there rain
uh winds, heavy winds, you know, with
dust control and so forth. But keeping
in mind that the cherry festival has
historically always operated on a rain
or shine event. So they would be taking
place anyways. The only thing is we
would have to make sure we mitigate
those uh impacts on this um if that were
to happen. Cost efficiencies like I
mentioned the Fourth of July fireworks
prep that's happening anyways. So you
would still need the fencing for that.
And if we were going to go ahead and do
the fencing, the cost for the fencing is
really the installation and the removal.
So, it really hasn't do not much to do
with the month-to-month. So, we'll keep
that on there. If the foundation ends up
paying for that, um, what we'll do is
we'll just pay the monthtomonth, which I
believe, uh, Robert, correct me if I'm
wrong. The monthly would be about $500 a
month roughly.
Okay. So, there wouldn't be much cost,
you know, if we had it for two
additional uh, months, you know, till
the end of the 4th of July.
Uh so again looking at all of these
costs
and looking at avoiding the rental
facility of 50,000
knowing that we have city-owned
equipment also to be able to provide and
help for that event like generators uh
third party rentals that we can help out
with. So all of this we feel are
feasible. Of course keep in mind that
the easy way to do it is to just keep
going with the Noble Creek. [laughter]
Um there is additional considerations
you know for the 30 acre sites and again
all costs right now are preliminary for
planning purposes only. Optional city
costs are included for transparency and
council direction. And again the final
costs between the city and foundation
would be subject to your direction and
any applicable agreements. If you wanted
us to amend theou to have other
considerations you know that's up for
discussion. Uh so all in all city has
approximately $219,000 budgeted 100,000
for the sponsorship 59,000 for traffic
control 14,000 for the weed abatement
10,000 for budget budgeted for the
fourth of July fencing
individual department overtime costs
6,000 for transit services and 30,000
for community services those are already
budgeted police department budgeted
63,000 in overtime costs um it also
shows this as revenue reimbursement. So
again, we can get this reimbured by the
foundation. And the other thing to keep
in mind, um this could be covered by the
economic development
budget. So economic development has uh
500,000 that are set aside for economic
uh promotional activities. If you
recall, this is something similar that
was done with Bulmont Knights. So if you
were to do this, we have that budget in
place. we could take from the 500,000 to
cover this. So, the additional impact of
the general fund, we're identifying
1936,
but 500,000 covered through the business
and center programs account. Um, so if
there's any questions that you have,
again, we're here to answer those as
well as the foundation. Our staff is
here. They work very diligently uh and
hard to put this together for you on a
timely basis. We do need uh an answer
today uh one way or the other. Thank
you.
All right. Thank you, Gus, uh, for that
and thank you to the staff for your hard
work in getting this together. I know we
kind of dropped that on. Yeah. Uh, do we
have any public comments on this item?
>> I have no written requests. And then, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> Right. Seeing none, I will open this up
to council discussion.
>> All right. Council member Martinez.
>> All right. Thank you. Uh, let's start
off with numbers just to make sure I
clarify. So the 412766
you're saying does not include the
100,000 anymore because that's now
covered. Correct. So that would be right
now what we would be looking at, you
know, at the planning level. But 412766.
>> That's correct. That 100,000 um could go
towards something else.
>> Okay. But I mean
>> Yeah. So the 412 then would be what it
costs with all those tallied up. um and
100,000 is not there because that's been
covered. So my question then for 25 when
you show that the total event cost is
was that with the $100,000?
>> I should say the 412 is um separate from
the 259,000
that were allocated last year. So the
412,000 does not take into account the
250,000.
>> Oh, I know that. But what I'm asking I
was trying to to compare. So this year
if we were to spend all that 412 without
getting reimbursed or whatever um that
would be what we're spending and then
last year we spent 259. Did we spend is
that 100,000 a part of that or is it 259
plus 100?
>> The 100,000 was part of the 259.
>> Okay. So then the difference then for
this year comes out to 152 more or less
um of an increase. And that's assuming
that that nothing's adjusted up there.
So, it brings us to my my second
question is the duplications that we saw
between the Cherry Foundation and our
costs like the restrooms and the fencing
and stuff that still needs to be
discussed to see who's going to do what
and what's going to come back and so
forth, right? So, that has to be
fine-tuned still.
>> That's correct, sir. And knowing that
the foundation has a total of 142,500
right now for the event, they're looking
to cover that gap, you know, for the
remainder. Um but also if they could
help out by not having the city pay for
the fencing fencing for instance that's
78,000 off of that 412.
>> Now the entertainment you say is covered
this year. Is that including as that
music and carnival? So I haven't seen
anything about carnival.
>> I believe it's just the music but uh we
do have um
>> here there was no carnival anywhere.
>> I think the carnival is separate but
we'll confirm. And then the question is
why if it is
>> Hi, good evening. Um the carnival is a
uh partner. We are contracted um in
partnership with them and they reimburse
us um a a settlement check um for their
revenue. So they are not um an expense
uh that comes out of the foundation's
budget at all.
>> Okay. So you don't rent them.
>> Correct.
>> Okay. So they come in and their money
comes off of their sales. Yes.
>> That they get. So foundation's not
taking a percentage or portion of those
sales.
>> No, the foundation takes a percentage of
the sales. We do not um contract them
and pay for them to be there. It's the
other way around.
>> So there's no expense, but there is
revenue.
>> Correct.
>> Okay. That that explains a lot. So I
appreciate that. Okay. Thank you. And
then Gus, um, so for the weather, you
know, I get concerned about having a
rainy rainy time and having a muddy
event. I know that we're at um, Stewart
Park, most of that was in grass, so I
mean, it gets soggy and stuff, but it
wouldn't get muddy. And then, um, at
Noble Creek, of course, you still had
the same grassy area except for the
Carnival was a lot of dirt and then most
of it was on pavement. So, we haven't
really for seen a cherry festival
totally on dirt um or whatever weeds are
there at that time. So, my concern is
what kind of mitigations would we be
able to do if any? You know, I don't
want it to be a Woodstock event where
we've got mud all over the place. So,
what would you say could [snorts] be
done if anything in that case?
>> Well, we could always have a mud run.
>> We might have we might have new carnival
things.
>> Yes. Well, [laughter] our public works
director and city engineer uh has
actually done a sample on a corner of
the site uh to look at three different
options of a discing. I'm going to turn
it over to uh Robert to explain what
that looks like.
>> Yeah, sure. So, the the leg of the
property closest to the school uh city
staff performed two separate
treatments, I guess, on two independent
acres of that that area. Uh we just
walked it today. We we did receive
substantial rain and on one of them we
compacted it so well that it it is still
stable. We were able to walk um
just fine. Didn't pick up too much dirt.
Barring uh a large storm event during
the event. I'm not sure what we'd be
able to do at that time. It is on dirt.
There there's not really a whole lot we
can do. However, the site did perform
very well under the rain that we just
received.
>> Would that be your prediction that it
would be able to hold the heaviness of
the carnival rides as well?
>> Uh I am not able to
>> that that was one of my concerns is that
I know for pedestrian walking that's one
thing but to have the ferris wheel and
stuff sitting on a dirt lot you know
that's not prepared or even if it is
prepared my concern is you know do we
have that contingency? Do we have the
ability to, you know, if they come in
and say it needs to have this
compaction? I don't know. I'm just
making things up. But it's a concern I
had. So,
>> I I don't have I don't have an
appropriate answer for you. What I do
have is that they do this
professionally. They do it all over.
They generally pick lots that are in
dirt of of comparable status.
>> So, they do an inspection beforehand and
let us know if there was something that
they didn't see was going to work. I'm
not able to
>> maybe the cherries of the past can uh
aid in that discussion.
[snorts]
>> Hi again. Yes, they do. um if they have
an engineer coming out um prior to
setting up uh where they map everything
and they um determine whether or not
it's a feasible lot, that is something
that we um can do even sooner than a
week or a couple days prior to um just
to make sure because I I also had the
same concern if the carnival rides would
be able to um withstand the dirt.
>> And that's two weeks prior to the event
or
>> we can we can do it earlier than that.
>> Okay. Yeah, but it it
normally it's about a week before.
>> Okay. Well, I might suggest an expedited
just just because we're on, you know, a
territory that we haven't been,
>> you know, though. Okay. I appreciate.
Thank you. And um the last question I
had might be for Cherries also.
>> Um my question had to do with the on a
part of the report it says that the
foundation's broader costs are not
included in the report. So, can you just
refer to what that means? Are is there
costs that you have like office expenses
and so forth that come out of Cherry
revenue
>> or do you have uh a separate revenue
source to cover those?
>> So, um yes, there are office expenses
and other foundation expenses that are
not included in the cherry festival
budget. Mhm.
>> Um so we do have
additional um
>> revenue source.
>> Do you have money coming in that pays
for that or do you use cherry money for
that? That's my question.
>> Historically it's always been cherry
festival revenue that has paid for um
all of the organization's um expenses.
So with our um new nonprofit status and
our new organization, we are trying to
um create more events to generate more
revenue so that way it offsets
foundation costs rather than having um
the cherry festival revenue off uh
paying for everything. And I appreciate
that because when you first brought that
up at the very beginning
>> last year or so that you were going to
try to do more things, my concern came
up was like, so you know, are we looking
at using cherry revenue for your those,
but it sounds like you're doing just the
opposite. You're trying to get that
revenue to cover instead of Yes.
>> All right. I appreciate that
clarification. That was a concern I had.
Thank you.
>> That's all, mayor.
>> All righty.
Uh, any other questions? Council member
Fen?
>> Yes. Um, so I'm a I apologize. I'm a
little confused by the numbers in that
if we were to not move it, what would
and and then we have and we'd spent 260
last year, what would we be looking at
or what would the charities of the past
be asking for a donation and, you know,
to help make the event happen?
If you were to continue with Noble
Creek, um right now that 100,000 that
you provided for the entertainment would
not be needed. However, they could ask
for that for something else to cover
other expenses,
>> which is the 122 or so that they are
short per shortfall. Okay.
>> Yes.
>> All right. So, if so, should we dec if
we decided to cover all of that?
We could we would it be a fair
comparison to say it's 122 to stay there
um at the parks district versus 412
by bringing it to our facility and then
that 412 could change in reference to
the fencing and and a couple other line
items in there. Correct.
>> Yes. The 78,000 and the 42,000 could go
away.
>> Okay. So then that would bring it down
to about 300.
>> Correct.
>> Okay. So 300 to move it 122 or so to
keep it there
>> viewed that way. Okay. All right. Thank
you.
>> I think one point of clarification that
I would have on that is that the 300
um looks like there's actually 219 that
will be going towards that 300. So you
would actually have 300 minus the 219
because of the sponsorship, the traffic
control, the weed abatement, the
fencing, the transit overtime, the
community services overtime, and the
police overtime have all been budgeted
essentially.
>> You make a really good point, Mary. That
is correct.
>> Okay. And then um
>> so on there's an attachment on here on
the relocation analysis which brings up
um the preliminary costs. So if you're
looking at what we are expediting, you
can see the 412 or we're putting out
there's a 10% contingency showing 412.
We currently have it budgeted at 219. So
this is what is currently budgeted is
the 219. So if you were to take the 412
minus the 219, you we as a city would
have a gap of 1937620
that we would need to to cover if the
fencing is picked up. So you have 193766
if the fencing is picked up at 73K
and the
>> the discing
>> the discing is picked up as a donation
which was
>> 42,000
>> 42 There we go.
>> Then that ends up at approximately 70 to
75K that we could then cover under the
GL budget
from community s or uh under the GL
>> for economic development
>> for economic development as a community
engagement um event and it would be
budgeted at 70 to 75,000. Really, my
suggestion would be that we probably
need to think about a h 100,000 uh and
wrap our minds around a h 100,000 that
would need to be expended out of this
community engagement fund to cover the
cherry festival there. So really we have
no impact to general fund except for
what's already programmed.
>> That's correct, mayor. And keeping in
mind that we did put that 37,524
contingency,
>> correct?
>> Which may not be used.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mayor.
you know, I just wanted to kind of
further um
just kind of bring up my thoughts on
this. Um, as we as we've discussed over
and over again with regards to these
events, it's it's nice to try and think
of a longer term plan. Um, and while I
want to feel like the police station
will be built in the next, let's say,
seven to 10 years, um, I think this
gives us a five-year plan. Um, and gives
us an opportunity to hold some other
events for now and at least gives us a
home for a little while while we think
about another home. Um, and I do think
that this gives us the opportunity for
Cherries of the Past to continue to grow
their program, which is what they're
really trying to to do. And I think that
what we've seen here uh in my opinion is
an excellent good faith effort by
charities of the past to continue to go
out and search other opportunities which
I don't think that we've seen in the
past. So it's very encouraging to see um
the potential donation for your
entertainment. Um and I think that I've
heard that they've been pounding the
pavement with a lot of different people
uh to try and get sponsorships. And more
than anything, I think that that good
faith goes a long way. And I want you
guys to be recognized for that because I
think that that takes a lot of work um
and a lot of grit. And I think you still
have the time to do it to even lower
cost potentially. Um and I think has
been mentioned numerous times on this
DIS that the city has really subsidized
this event for a long time and we didn't
really recognize that at the beginning.
Um, and I do know that while we're
putting a lot of pressure on
um on our staff to do something of this
um size and nature, I I know that our
staff um and I have full confidence that
they believe in this event and that they
want to see it to be successful as well.
And I think with the partnership, we can
really bring uh an event that knocks it
out of the park. Um, oh, probably a poor
choice.
[laughter]
>> Wow, good one.
>> Um,
and I just think that we really have
some great opportunities um to continue
to develop this partnership. I really
do. [snorts]
>> Uh, Council Member Lara.
>> Yes. Um, I'm sorry. Can I get you back
up again? That the representative I've
forgotten your name. I
Yes,
>> I want to just echo the mayor's comments
and your efforts. I understand that
you've already replanned the layout of
the carnival as well.
>> I did.
>> Uh you've already gotten the sponsorship
of the entertainment. So that kudos to
you for that.
>> Thank you.
>> So let me ask you, are you comfortable
with moving this this project or did I
put you on the spot?
>> A little bit.
>> Okay. Um I I would like to speak for all
of my board. Um my executive board, my
board of directors. Um there is some
hesitancy. Uh we're concerned about um
environmental um concerns
of is it going to be feasible? Is it
going to be ready in time? Me
personally, um, with the determination
that the city staff has put into it
already, um, I feel like they are
really, really devoted to wanting to get
it done and have it be successful. Um,
so I think
I think we just want we want the
festival to happen. We want it to
succeed. Um, and I when I say succeed, I
I I literally probably just mean like
have opening day happen and have people
come in like
>> as long as that um is everybody's goal.
Um, I I personally think that it could
be possible. Um, but that doesn't mean
that I don't have hesitations or
concerns.
>> Sure. I think I think as you can tell,
we all do, right? I mean, it's it's
something that's new. We're going into
territory that we've never ventured into
before either. But I think that as the
mayor indicated, I think there's an
opportunity for a great partnership
here.
>> I agree.
>> Um, one of the concerns that I've had
for years is, you know, how does this
how do we sustain this? And I think
maybe we're looking at a potential
option of of sustaining this and
hopefully it's the beginning of
something new. So,
>> I just wanted to commend you for your
efforts though and thank the board for
their support.
>> Thank you. I will definitely take that
back to them.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> That's all I have, Mayor.
>> Thank you, Council Member White or Mayor
Prom, excuse me. Uh that's okay. Uh so
first of all for the knock it out of the
park comment that's jvo gt at
bulmontca.go.
[laughter]
[clears throat]
>> Um
>> did you guys see the speed bump that I
[laughter]
>> the uh the cleanup? Um I know that was a
concern that parks district had. So, is
the cleanup something that staff's going
to be responsible for the Cher's
Foundation
or do we need to just think about that
and add it to the to the list?
>> That was factored in the community
services overtime budget.
>> Correct.
>> Okay. As added.
>> And u in response to one of your
comments, Mr. Martinez,
where's the grass at Steuart Park?
>> Okay. Okay. because I did it's always
been dirt there for me. Um, council
member Laura pointed out there is some
grass around the pool or was. But
anyways, um,
and if there is a huge large storm, I
would imagine the I hate to say this,
but I would imagine the attendance is
going to be way down, you know, if it if
it's just full on what we had the last
day or two. So, I'm not real concerned
about that. And I also I think we've got
a plan in place as far as making sure
that the ground meets the needs of the
Carnival people. You know, this is a
decision that I don't take lightly. I
don't think any of us do given the
additional cost, but our responsibility
is not to choose the cheapest option.
It's to choose the most reliable and
most defensible. Uh the district has
twice failed to honor specific terms
under which we agreed to hold the cherry
festival.
Once may be a miscommunication, twice
establishes a pattern. Proceeding again
without enforcable insuranceances would
reflect a breakdown in oversight. Um,
spending an additional $150,000,
$200,000, whatever that number is is
difficult, but doing so to ensure
certainty and accountability is risk
mitigation and not ma, not waste. And at
this point, the issue is not trust, it's
governance. So, uh, continuing under the
same conditions to me would not be
optimism. It would be negligence. And I
think we need to move forward with
moving this to, um, the city's property.
That's all I had.
>> All right. I will entertain a motion.
Um, looks like this is a receive and
file and to provide the direction. So, I
guess we don't really need a motion. We
need to provide direction. I'm assuming
that there needs to be modifications to
theou.
Um,
>> yes, and that's something we'll be
talking with staff and the board about
foundation. Uh, but we do need direction
as to whether you want to continue at
Noble Creek or move forward with the 30
acre site.
>> You know, I personally think it should
be a motion.
>> There should be a motion as well.
>> So, I'll I'll move that we uh go the uh
way of the city property at Bowmont and
Cougar.
>> I'll second.
>> Can I get a roll call, please? Council
member Laura,
>> yes.
>> Council member Finn,
>> Council member Martinez,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Pro Tim White,
>> Mayor Voy,
>> yes.
>> All righty, let the adventure begin.
>> At least we can have full direction and
a plan. All right, we'll be moving on to
item J4, and this is a follow-up report
uh number 20 for our local state of
emergency sewer mainline failure and
emergency repairs in Fairway Canyon. and
we will have a staff report by Thaxton
Vanbell.
>> Good evening, Mayor and Council. Um,
these items uh have been a uh
reoccurring staff report since the
incident uh March of last year. We are
uh at a point where
we have hit the $1 million budget on
paper and therefore this has become an
action item to request
uh city manager authority for an
additional $100,000.
As of today, we're out of pocket
540,000.
We have incumbrances
that would total 1,28,000.
That would be if we spent every dime of
contingency, extra mitigation, etc. The
wild card in all of this is uh any
continued legal fees. U Miss Mendoza
shared with me this morning that we have
about $5,000 in legal fees that is not
reflected at the time of the staff
report. So the 28,000
um
does not reflect those totals we just
got today. So, uh, [clears throat]
that's why we're here with this on as an
action item.
>> All right. Do we have any public comment
on this item?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All righty. And uh I will open it up for
council discussion but for just one
point of clarification uh so the extra
funds the 100,000 that we are requesting
for the grand total of 1.1 million do we
feel like this is going to be adequate
to cover the fees moving forward
uh with the new information you've been
given? Sorry, I should have added that
caveat.
I mean, that that still gives us about
a, you know, roughly a $70,000 buffer. I
I I feel like we're at the end. Um,
construction has started for the final
repair. Um, obviously the rain this week
is uh put a pause on it, but I I think
this will be wrapped up in a couple
weeks. What I can answer is how far and
how long the legal portion will drag
out. that because they all they're
dealing with the insurance company and
and other items like that kind of
outside of the direct um advice and
repair.
>> Do you know what we I mean besides the
500 that you just mentioned is that the
total in legal fees that we have
acquired I know we have a special lawyer
at this point.
>> Um just to be clear that's not just
legal fees that is the initial response
construction that's the renting the
pumps and it's the so that's what we've
actually outlaid out of pocket. We still
have a commitment for a contract of, you
know, the the the next um 300 plus
thousand to do the final repairs and
then things like contingency, ongoing
mitigation, things like that.
>> Okay. Just trying to see if you have
another number that you'd like to say.
Well, there's a chance that we won't
even hit the million, but
>> we are currently encumbered for 1,28,15,
so we don't want to move forward without
uh authorization.
>> Very good. Any further council
discussion?
I will entertain a motion.
Mayor, I'll make a motion to wave the
full reading and adopt by title only a
resolution of the city council of the
city of Bulmont extending the
declaration of a local emergency and
authorizing the city manager to take
action increase the spending authority
of the city manager by 100,000 for a
grand total of 1,100,000
to be used uh to address this emergency
sewer mainline fail.
>> I'll second.
>> All right. Can I get a roll call,
please?
>> Council member Laura.
>> Yes.
>> Council member Finn.
>> Yes. Council member Martinez,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Pro Tim White,
>> Mayor Voy,
>> yes.
>> All right, everybody doing okay up
there?
>> All right, we will move on to J5,
recycle water update. Uh, Mr. Van Bell
as well.
>> Okay, this uh item today is a um
receive and file. It's a it's uh as
requested. It's kind of a recap of uh
recycled water specifically, you know,
what what's still ahead of us. Um but to
to know where you're going, you kind of
have to know where you've been. So
within here, we have a recap. We have a
really high level. Um things really
started going getting going in 2018. Um
when uh city council brought on staff,
um
approved the plans, did the kickoff for
the the new plant, the brine line. etc.
And there's multiple moving parts here.
So I think um one area um some of the
feedback I get is confusion over brine
line and recycled water. So I'd like to
address that one specifically.
The brine line it is a serves as a
byproduct to create the recycled water
and also satisfy the state's
anti-degradation
uh limits that they published in 2015.
2015 they said you got to take the salt
out of the groundwater.
Bumont did not do that at that time and
then that became what we call our salt
mortgage. So we kind of owe the debt all
the way back to then. And all of that is
handled through the plant's reverse
osmosis facility and the reject water
goes down the brine line which runs from
here to San Bernardino and then it ties
into the Inland Empire brine line that
actually takes that water all the way to
Orange County for treatment.
So that forecast that we owe um we are
currently projecting to first quarter of
2028 to be satisfied with that.
If we were to stop discharging in the
creek, we couldn't make up
the the debt because we wouldn't be
putting the the clean water in there. So
we're so there's kind of one um marker
in the ground. You we have to get past
that. We owe that. At any time if we
fail to meet that, they will come back
and institute all fines dating back to
2015. So our full intention is to
satisfy that and we're well on the way.
The next is the environmental and I use
that as a giant umbrella.
In order to pull our water out of the
creek,
we get involved with the division of
water rights. Uh a few years ago,
myself, city staff, and a couple council
persons went up, talked to the state
board in Sacramento, and at that time,
they indicated we'd need to do an
environmental study that we call an
AMMP, a mitigation plan,
and that's to look at the effect of
pulling your water out of the creek.
What's it going to do to the riperian
habitat?
We came back, we got an approval um to
uh have somebody start on that plan.
It's an environmental study, so the
first year is to get the baseline. And
this kind of goes in with the time when
you're when you're looking at the
effects of habitat. These studies have
to go year round. It's not just what's
happening in five minutes or a month or
they're they're year-long studies for
that, you know, the birds, the nesting,
the different, um, species of plants
that are growing, etc.
Uh, recently,
um, as we've moved forward and getting
ready to file that change petition,
we were told we'd have to perform what's
called a full environmental study or
SQA. We hear that all the time. SQA goes
beyond just what the water is going to
do. It's not just the lo the loss of the
water by diverting it for a recycle
project. It takes into account things
like if we have to build a pump station
to move the water, how much electricity,
carbon, etc. If we have to build a
pipeline from here to somewhere else in
town, what are the environmental
impacts, greenhouse gas, etc. And that's
where we are now.
Um tonight we have um Clay Sorenson with
uh West Yoast. Uh they are performing
the AMMP. They performed the first
portion. They we did the um the report
and they are continuing now. We have
engaged them to do the uh the squa and
they've wrapped that into their um their
total package. So Clay's got a few
slides here to kind of talk about where
we are and and where we're going and
what's involved. And with that, I'll
turn it over to Clay.
Good evening, Mayor and Council. Thank
you for having me. Um, I just have a few
slides to present to kind of give the
overview and update on this project.
[clears throat]
Um, so there'll just be three main
slides here. wanted to give the overview
and purpose um a few accomplishment
highlight a few accomplishments um and
then discuss the path forward and next
next steps.
Um [snorts] so as Thaxon mentioned
there's a ton of um steps you have to
take uh to get to your your main goal up
in the upper right here of utilizing uh
treated waste water as recycled water in
Bowmont, California.
Um so the past year and a half we uh
spent a lot of time there's a lot of
data in this area um which has actually
set up the city of Bowmont very well for
for future steps um to characterize both
the riparian and hydraologic systems. Um
we're currently setting up the baseline
monitoring program which is which is
outlined in that uh baseline um excuse
me the
historical characterization report.
[snorts] Um we've been uh beginning uh
the taking steps to file the SQA
documents um which is also a large
amount of of um work and a lot of
technical studies that go into that. Um,
another document that uh, Thaxton
mentioned um, and is required by the
state board uh, and will help uh,
certain a um, appease certain agencies
to not petition this project uh, is
called the adaptive management and
mitigation plan. [snorts] Um,
[clears throat] and it's it's something
that can actually be called out as a
mitigation measure within SQA.
Um and as as Thaxton mentioned, what it
will do is is outline any potential
impacts to riparian
um you know from a reduction in surface
water flow and how those will be
managed, monitored and mitigated.
Um so one of the last steps here um and
probably one of the more significant
ones is the change petition to the state
board that that um that document itself
really requires those squa documents as
well as the AMMP.
Um and then once that's uh accept
submitted and accepted by the state
board uh there would be some ongoing
monitoring uh through the AMMP document.
Um but that could likely occur
um you know after that that recycled
water is is able to be utilized.
Um again wanted to highlight some of the
accomplishments um and and uh steps
we've taken uh to to where we're at
today. Um so talked a little bit about
uh the characterization report. Um as
well uh as well mentioned the uh
baseline monitoring program that's
outlined in that report. Uh at the end
of last year, we helped the city secure
a grant from the DWR
um to install a few stream gauges um so
reducing overall project costs to the
city. Uh we begin we've began the SQA
process and and one of our project team
members uh Caitlyn with Tom Dodson is is
leading that effort. Um
and then um to set the project up for
success, we've engaged a number of
regulatory agencies including the state
board and the California Department of
Fish and Wildlife.
Um and today I was actually visiting a
few of the potential stream gauge sites.
So we're well into setting up uh the
baseline monitoring program.
Um so this is ba a pretty high level
timeline of um what we've done and where
we're headed um and given some general
time uh frames on when they will be
completed. Uh and I think if you want a
more detailed
um overview of the different tasks that
go into each of these, you can find it
in the uh uh agenda or board packet.
Thank you.
Thank you, Clay. Yeah, I think a couple
of the the highlights there to are that
we are we're doing things like engaging
um fish and wildlife now instead of the
first time talking them after we file.
Um if we if we get them on board as
we're going um make sure it satisfies
everything.
Those are the kind of steps we're taking
now
so that we don't get held up later. It
does take more time. You know, you have
to interface with them. We have um
meetings set up. We uh do feedback, you
know, back and forth, etc. But it's
better than them coming in after we
finished everything and hitting us, you
know, with something out of left field
saying,
you know, we object and then and then
we're out there trying to gather uh and
and start over again. So, uh I I know
it's a lengthy process. I know sometimes
it, you know, it doesn't feel like
things are happening. We don't, it's not
a building, so you don't see a lot
getting graded. You don't see a
foundation getting poured. You don't
see, you know, um, structures going up,
but there's there's a lot of activity
happening in the background. And then,
uh, finally,
you know, we we have engaged our our
local partners. you know, we we recently
kicked off the project with the PASS
agency for a sighting study for
groundwater recharge um when we get to
that point. And then um we continue to
work with Bulmont Cherry Valley on anou
for the use of the water and purple pipe
and possibly moving it. Bulmont Cherry
Valley also provided feedback on this uh
squa project because they would be a
partner. So, with that, um, I'll open to
questions or comments from council and,
uh, as is Clay.
>> Thank you very much for that report. We
appreciate you being here as well. And,
uh, Nicole, do we have any uh, public
comment?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All righty. I will open that up to
council discussion and start with Mayor
Promite.
>> Uh, thanks for the report. Um, and I
agree a lot of stuff is being worked on
and and I also agree it seems to take a
lot longer than it should. Um,
but I'm not a water guy. Um, so Mike,
the concern I have, let me ask a couple
questions.
>> Okay. Um, when we talk about the agency
repair and uh mitigation,
bottom line, if if if
someone downstream is impacted by our
changing how much water's going down the
stream, then we have to mitigate that or
go through a legal process. Correct.
>> Yeah. when you actually file the change
petition, uh it's published and there's
an open period for anyone essentially to
come and, you know, file,
you know, a a uh an objection.
>> Okay. And I think you brought up the
fact that one of the processes, and I'm
not sure which one, um involved trying
to to lessen that impact of of having to
mitigate by getting ahead of the game on
that.
>> Yeah. And that's what so much of the
study is is to make sure and you know
and and that you're not impacting in a
negative way the environment. Um many of
the if I look at other uh local agencies
that have been that have had objections.
There's a few uh environmental groups
that are out there and they pretty much
just cart blanc will file one. But the
first one is always California uh
Department of Fish and Wildlife. I mean,
that's going to be your first their
internal there. If if you haven't worked
with them, that's going to be a serious
um hold up for sure.
>> And what role does our um water master
play in any of this?
>> Um
really at this level, really none.
>> Okay. Um, and it is likely Ukipa Valley
Water District would be one of the our
biggest concerns as far as um the
rumblings we already hear as far as what
may happen once uh we limit the amount
of water that's going down there.
Anyone downstream has a potential
um
to to to throw their hat in the ring, so
to speak. There are things like, you
know, water from outside of basin going
to another basin and that that's again
that's another legal group that we have
uh on on board.
>> But doesn't the water master manage the
the basin issues?
>> The water master
uh deals with
groundwater levels in the adjudicated
portion of the basin.
for what we're looking to do that water
wouldn't necessarily
leave that that area. We would be using
the water our current proposal is to use
the water within the basin. Okay. Okay.
That's all I had. Thank you.
>> One question for you. Um it seems like I
don't know I like to be a mediator
sometimes. So it seems like there's a
way in which you send some down the
creek, right? And then you you you put
some back in. So is that part of what
the study is doing then to look at and
say if I send 60% down the creek and I
recycle 40% and monetize it, then that's
where we're at. And it's going to give
us all of those options and the
mitigation at each point. That is
exactly what we're doing in part of the
first phase study. And we had a couple
we were kind of at a fork in the road as
these studies go. And one of the items
we came to council with was the initial
findings of the study supported
pulling out anything in excess of a rate
of 1.7 MGD daily.
So there's already some scientific
support that everything downstream of us
would be supported in the same way that
it is today by leaving that roughly 40
to 50% flow
going downstream.
>> Right. Excellent. Thank you. I think
there's always a way forward with some
type of compromise and you know finding
out those. So, I appreciate the work
that's going in and I'm sure that that's
what those monitors uh in the stream
beds at strategic points down the line
are doing.
>> And that's exactly the intent. If we
just came in one day and said, "We're
taking it all," you'd have everybody
lined up.
>> Sure.
>> with their pitchforks and torches. And I
know that with the amount of money that
we put into recycled water, it is
important to recoup
um you know at the highest point
possible so that we can uh reap those
benefits. And I think that that's
something that we need to be continually
balancing is, you know, how we find uh
that sweet spot for a lack of better
terms um to be able to, you know, we put
forth a lot of cash for the
infrastructure and now we need to make
sure that we are being responsible uh
with what we are doing. And I I think
that's really the key point that we need
to hold on to is that it was a lot that
we fronted and we need to make sure that
we're looking at the best way to ensure
that we are paying that back in a
fiscally responsible way. Uh council
member Fen.
>> Yeah. Quick question. [clears throat]
Thank is there a point at which if we
don't if we're not able to recover
enough that it's just not financially
feasible to pursue it any further. Um
you mentioned the 1.7 that's million
gallons a million gallons of water per
day. Correct.
>> Per day.
>> So if we continue that do do we have the
potential of
as the city continues to grow expect
more water to go through the system. So
therefore then we can if we we maintain
that 1.7 then we have more than to
recover. And and is there a potential of
hey we're not going to have enough. This
doesn't make sense. pull the plug now.
It's not worth spending the money. We're
not looking at that, are we?
>> Well,
>> I mean, are are we looking at it, but
we're not not necessarily going to run
into that issue?
>> I would argue that the money's spent.
>> Okay.
>> The the plant is functioning, the
water's being produced. Now, it's the
effort to keep it. And then, um, I'd be
remiss if I didn't quote, uh, Mr.
Jaggers with his conservation of a way
of life, things coming in the future
that there's a threat that even as we
grow as a city, there may be less and
less water that actually comes uh to the
plant through the pipes as new state
laws cause tighter and tighter
restrictions on things like your
showerheads, your toilets, your faucets,
etc., etc.
>> Okay. At least at least we're got our
eye open to it. So, all right. Thank
you.
>> All right. Very good. Any last comments
from council?
Okay. Thank you both. We appreciate
that.
>> Thank you.
>> Sure. All right. We will move on to J6,
city population and wayfinding signage.
Uh staff report by Julie Van Hook.
>> I'll take this one, Julie.
>> Thank you.
>> You can kick it off. [laughter]
Can I get it to share my screen?
>> Yeah, a few slides.
So, on January 20th, uh staff prepared a
provided a recap of prior efforts
related to the downtown revitalization
plan. And during the discussion, council
expressed interest in two related items.
replacing the city's outdated population
signs and developing a coordinated
wayfinder sign signage [clears throat]
program. Just a brief note on population
and elevation signs. They serve as more
than just markers. They provide a quick
standardized information about our
community. Population signs give
residents and visitors a sense of scale,
helping them understand local resources
and infrastructure.
Elevation signs are equally important,
offering a geographic data that supports
weather awareness, emergency response,
and safety, especially in areas prone to
flooding or altitude related health
concerns. Together, these signs
reinforce our civic identity and provide
essential information for both residents
and visitors.
A note on wayfinding signs. Wayfinding
signs play a critical role in guiding
people to key destinations such as
downtown civic facilities, parks,
cultural assets, and public parking.
As we continue our downtown
revitalization and economic development
efforts, clear and consistent wayfinding
signs will improve navigation, enhance
the visitors experience,
and strengthen our city's brand.
Attractive standardized signage creates
a sense of place and support tourism and
local business growth. The list on the
right is a tentative destination
proposed is the tentative destinations
proposed to be highlighted. The
communication division in coordination
with staff has developed a conceptual
design aligned with the downtown
revitalization plan. The city's PIO
Julie Van Hook will discuss the design.
Thank you, Robert. Um, so council, what
you see before you is kind of an ad
adaptation of what you saw in the
downtown revitalization plan. Um, it's
reinforcing our city branding. Um, and
these are some proposed design concepts
for both population and wayfinding. And
like Robert had mentioned, it's for, um,
navigation, um, for more welcoming
environment and to create a kind of
safer, easier way to travel in town. And
so what you see in front of you is um an
example some some variations there um um
of using our city branding colors and
some sample um areas that we would
highlight. Um and tonight we're seeking
um you know your general input and
direction on whether staff should
proceed with the design concepts or some
adaptation thereof.
I'm up. Um all right. Do we have any
public comment? Thank you, Julie. And
Mr. Vestal,
>> I have no written requests. Someone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All right. Well, I will open it up to
council's discussion. Council member
Fen.
>> All right. This is a joke. Mayor,
welcome to the tile discussion. I know
you guys as I was reading this I was
like I do I I I don't want I've already
messed up today once so I'm going to
keep my comments quiet. Um but
>> I do I do have a little bit more. Thank
you. Go for it.
>> Uh Robert, our elevation is that um how
is that determined? Is that the location
of city hall or the highest point within
the city?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. So I did
pull it from city hall. Our differential
throughout the city is hundreds of feet.
So it is city hall.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you. Um,
no. I on Can you pull it the the the
signs back up? Um,
so if I had a preference, um, I'm
leaning towards, um, three and four just
to start the conversation. I'm good for
now, Mayor.
>> All right. Very good. Uh, Council Member
Lara.
>> Well, thank you very much for putting
this together for us. Uh, I I also like
number four. Um, on the monument sign,
this is just for
wayfinding, right? It's not entry
monuments. Those are separate. That's a
different type of a
structure. Correct.
>> Yes.
>> So, of the A, B, C, and D, I like B, but
I'd like to know which is the
easiest to maintain
of these because I I don't want
something like E looks like that'd be
very difficult to maintain. You got a
photo may fade out. I want something
that looks good for an extended period
of time that's easy to maintain. I don't
mind the slumpstone block on on B or
even if you do like a port and paste
concrete. Maybe this stamped. I don't
know. But um what would be easiest to
maintain for long-term purposes?
>> I I think the difference would be
negligible.
>> Okay.
>> Um if you want the absolute easiest,
it's going to be C and D. However, the
maintenance on A and B, like I said, is
is negligible.
>> Okay. I like Well, I like B. And that
could either be on a port and paste
concrete or the lumpstone. either one.
>> Wonderful. And just to note too for
council that brick uh matches the
monument in the front for the memorial
plaza. We have pillars and so it's the
same type of brick that we're going to
use cohesively. If you went with the
brick or you know you were leaning
towards that aspect.
>> Thank you.
>> That's all I have here.
>> Council member White.
>> Um I have two comments. Number one, um
I'm going to defer to my colleagues on
the colors and uh shapes and sizes. And
my second comment is we should
definitely limit this to 30 minute
discussion.
>> Okay.
>> Sure. Sure.
>> I I I do like four because it's already
got two votes.
>> So [laughter] if we can move on, I'll go
with four.
>> All right. Council member Martinez,
let's roll the dice.
>> Quick question on the A and B. Are those
um closer to the ground?
>> Yes.
>> Is Is that what that shows? So similar
to what we have right now, maybe in
front of Stater Brothers and so it's a
little closer.
>> Much?
>> Yeah. I prefer taller myself as I do
find that a little bit hard to see
sometimes as you're going. You have to
kind of look down. Um especially if you
put a rock in front of it. But um
>> the [laughter]
but
uh so anyway, I'm okay with um four. I
do like three or four. I'm not gonna,
you know, I'm okay with really anything.
I just like the higher rather than the
lower.
>> Okay. Well, very good. Well, um I don't
I don't want to continue to drag this
out by any means. I do though, however,
want to go back to the list of suggested
uh places. And I want to highlight that
I appreciate the addition of some of our
other governmental uh groups with the
library as well as Noble Creek. Um, and
so as I was reading through those, I
started to think about uh people coming
as visitors into the city. And so I
would like to suggest that potentially
we just add the high school there um as
people come to see uh other events at
the high school uh and is a is a
destination and since we've included two
of our other partners, it might be a
good idea to include them as well. And
uh I was leaning towards three, but
since four seems so popular, we can go
with four. And I too like B as well.
Do we need any other direction?
>> Uh, mayor, I had only mentioned four. So
if we go back to the other one, um, the
other slide, how how tall would we
expect be to be off the ground?
>> Three feet.
>> No, it'll be more like four or five when
it's full. All right. So, I'm good with
B as well.
And we're thinking about those in um
main entry points. Is that what we're
thinking for those kind of monument?
Okay.
>> So the the red represents where you'd
see those the the lettered monuments,
the population, and then the blue
represents the wayfinders.
We also could combine
>> for the red the wayfinding and the
population signs.
we have that option just because some of
the spots are duplicative and for visual
clutter. Um we just need to kind of see
a design physically to actually see can
we can we read what we want them to read
and is it too much for them to read in
in one location. So there is that option
too.
Yeah, I was going to say the one other
thing is we have a lot of options there.
We don't necessarily need to see them
all on one. Um so that might you know
just be something to think about as
well. So, it seems like we've gone with
B and with four
and then I imagine you guys will bring
back a more refined discussion with
costs and things along those lines.
>> We can So, we do anticipate developing a
CIP for these
uh which you'll see at the fiscal year.
>> Okay. Does council want to see the
design or are you happy with moving
forward with four MB and allowing the
PIO to um exercise her judgment.
>> Are we good with that?
>> Yeah.
>> May the force be with you.
>> Have fun, Julie. [laughter]
>> All righty. Uh so do we have enough
direction and we'll see that back as a
CIP. Okay. Very good. [snorts] So, we
will keep this rolling. J7, our 202526
midyear.
Am I going in the right? Yes. Midyear
budget report. Uh, Miss Station
>> and you guys didn't even need a 30
minute time frame
>> because I kept the choices. Just give us
two choices.
>> I was really looking forward to some
longer discussion.
>> We can bring it back.
>> Nope.
>> All right. We are all set.
>> All right. Great. Oh, slides are up,
too. Okay.
So, we're'll be presenting the 202526
midyear budget report. We're going to go
over a quick economic update, general
fund status, revenue and expenses,
wastewater fund status, transit fund
status, and recommended budget
amendments.
So starting with our economic update,
the US economy remains stable entering
2026 with GDP growth around 2.5%.
And inflation moderating to 2.7%,
unemployment is slightly higher at 4.6%
but still historically healthy. [snorts]
Um [clears throat] while recession risk
is low in the near term, rising federal
debt and potential asset market
volatility present longer term risks. Um
overall there is not an expected uh
recession according to Beacon Economics.
As far as uh the California economy
goes, California's unemployment rate is
higher at 5.6% with growth uh
concentrated in healthcare and
government. Housing affordability and
policy uncertainty continue to be um to
constrain expansion and the state's
reliance on capital gains revenue also
creates ongoing budget volatility.
The overall takeaway is that conditions
are stable today, but long-term fiscal
caution remains appropriate.
Uh going to our local economy, the
unemployment rate in the Riverside,
Sanino, Ontario region was 5.2% in
December 2025. And that's slightly
improved from November, but still above
last year's 4.9% level. Riverside County
is at 5.2% in Sanino County at 5%.
Locally, permit activity declined in
calendar year 2025 and is down 15.9%
compared to 2024, indicating a
moderation in development activity. Um,
the overall takeaway for our local
economy is the regional labor market
remains stable, but development activity
has slowed compared to last year.
And now before I go into general fund,
I'll just stop and see if there are any
questions.
Okay, continue.
>> Mayor, we have a quick question. So,
back to the the slide for the permits
that were pulled. Do we have any numbers
from the county, you know, countywide
and how do we compare to that? Do you
know?
>> I do not have those numbers, but Steph
might be able to grab those.
>> Okay. because I know that just in
general, you know, a lot of our new home
neighborhoods are reaching near sold
out. We've got one that's going to have
grand opening coming up, but our heyday
is kind of over, you know, for now. Um,
so I think that probably reflected in
that, but I still think there's probably
a lot of regional growth still going on
in in Riverside County. Um,
>> Gotcha. Yeah. Okay. Uh that's probably
something that staff can maybe are um
planning or building
>> just just as a comparison to say okay if
we've you know if we're comparing
unemployment and so forth you know and
different things you know county to
state and then we if we looking at
permits then if we see a drop or an
increase how are we doing with with the
county
>> right gotcha
>> you know as a as a comparison thanks
>> okay for general fund overview as of
December 31st 2025 general fund revenues
total 21.8 million. That's down 21% from
last year. Uh that's largely due to
timing differences in prior one-time
revenues. Expenditures total 27.5
million, up 12% from last year at
midyear. It is important to note that
several major revenue sources, including
property taxes, are received in the
second half of the fiscal year.
Historically, the city relies on its 16%
operating reserves during the first six
months to manage cash flow and avoid
short-term borrowing. Taxes account for
approximately 69% of the general fund,
primarily property tax, sales tax, and
other local taxes. Um, overall takeaway
is mid-year performance reflects timing
differences and reserves continue to
support stable cash flow management.
For general fund revenues, sales tax
remains one of the city's largest
revenue sources. Midyear collections are
lower than that last year, and that's
primarily due to a onetime 6.2 2 million
audit correction received in the last
fiscal year um which was not included in
this year's budget numbers. We knew that
they were one-time um audit finding.
Additional sales tax revenue from
November and December will post in the
third quarter of the current fiscal
year. Property taxes are currently at
33% of budget was which is typical since
most receipts occur in the second half
of the fiscal year. Other taxes are up
16% year-over-year and franchise fees
are up slightly at 2%.
And as you can see, it's kind of hard to
see all the the different columns or the
different years on the other taxes.
Taxes is a majority of the revenue
sources. So, um it's it's much larger in
comparison to the other other sources
that are on here.
Uh general fund expenditures and uses of
funds are 27.5 million or 36% at midyear
and this represents 11.5% or a 2.85
million increase from the same point
last year. Um and as you can see the
largest uh expenditure for the general
fund is personnel um and then operating
and then uh the others are are smaller
amounts.
The following chart is where departments
stand at the major point. Departments
that are highlighted are either uh plus
50% 10 10% or um less 10% from the 50%
mark. So those have been highlighted
just so that you can see um and I'll
I'll pause here to see if there are any
questions before I move forward.
>> Can you explain that last um column you
just mentioned? Go tell me again what
the yellow is and the
>> the percentage of budget. So that's
that's if you are over under by more
than 10% from your midway point. So
you're either less than 40% or you're
above 60%. So that would mean that
you're just you're not tracking right on
to the 50%.
>> Okay.
>> And Jennifer, is that um increase in
personnel due to the healthcare increase
recent or increase in personnel numbers?
>> We did increase our our um FTE counts.
>> Okay. last fiscal year. So it would be a
portion of that as well as your other
regular increases that occur from year
to year. So it could be um step
increases and and and and health cost.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> So your question was in reference to the
76% for risk and HR or
>> well yeah basically but I think I
understand where it's at.
>> Can you speak a little bit more to that?
Um, correct [snorts] me if I'm wrong,
but HR and risk, there's a backend
allocation that occurs probably midy
year at the end of the year for an
allocation over to one of the special
funds that we oversee as well as part of
that.
>> Is this typical for this time of year
>> that for HR and risk, it's it's typical
for that year.
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Risk and HR. So, and that's your um a
lot of it too is is the insurance
payment is at the very beginning of the
fiscal year. So, it's a a very large
onetime cost out of the budget. So
usually that budget's mostly spent by
the time it comes to the the middle
[clears throat] of the year.
>> But the increase though between years is
due to the increase in FTEEs.
>> That that would be for the personnel.
That would be correct.
>> Okay.
>> May I have to Yeah.
>> Can you go back a slide?
>> Sure.
>> One more.
>> The investment earnings, what's the uh
2324? How what was that spike there? So
[cough] with investment earnings um I
will say in this fiscal year there is
and I don't want to get too technical
but um accounting has to do a entry to
marktomarket is what they call um so you
would essentially have to if as interest
rates rise essentially your portfolio
value goes down even though you would
never recognize that you would hold your
you'd hold your investments up until a
point of maturity but Gatsby requires
you to make that adjustment in your in
your financials. um something I don't
necessarily agree with because you're
not going to necessarily do it, but they
have you do it. I will tell you that in
our current fiscal year, we have
received about 850,000 investment
earnings, but it's not recognized
because of that um adjusting entry. So,
you might see that increase later on at
the end of the year once we start um
re-justing for what happens during this
current fiscal year. So, you're talking
about project projected um interest
rates, but over the last year, aren't
the interest rates down from what they
were a year ago?
>> They they are. They have decreased, but
you'll see that that it was it was
opposite in prior years. So, you had low
interest rates, but a higher market
value.
>> Got it. Okay. Thank you,
Council
>> Ortitz, do you still have? I'm done.
Thank you.
>> Okay. Go ahead.
Okay. So, um we estimate our results. Um
and these are just estimates, but
general general fund revenues are
projected to come in above budget by 6.7
million, mostly due to HTL projections
of higher sales tax than budget. General
fund expenditures are projected to have
savings of roughly 3.6 6 million and
that would result in a net amount above
budget of an estimated 10.3 million.
Um and then our fund balance for the
general fund, the unassigned fund
balance at the start of the fiscal year
was 26.8 million. This balance is your
available reserves. Um but we have made
some adjustments to that already within
the current fiscal year. So a
reappropriation of un unexpended
expenditures from fiscal year 2425
was adjusted in the amount of 618,000.
On August 19th, 2025, the city council
approved a CIP budget amendment to
program 800,000 of the assigned reserves
reserves balance to the Petro CIP
project.
And there has been an amount um set
aside and as you'll see later on in the
slide we have a budget amendment
requested for uh 68,000 set aside forou
required bonus payment from the fiscal
year 202425 audited financial results.
The current available fund balance this
is your savings account. These are like
your rainy day funds
um account is at 24.9 million and
unprogrammed revenue. So this is your
checking basically like your checking
account where you know the money comes
in and goes out available funds of
$66,446.
>> Jennifer before you move on a quick
question for you. Can you uh let us know
with this savings account what is that
percentage are in our reserves
currently? Are we at the 16% or is it
higher than that? So, in total, I don't
have it calculated just for your on your
available balance, but in total, which
would include your 16% working capital
cash flow, you have a $5 million budget
stabilization reserve as well as a $1
million emergency reserve. With those
reserves plus what you have available
for spending, it's about 61%.
>> 61. Thank you.
And um the uhou bonus pay I think we all
know what that is but can you explain
that for someone who may not know what
that is?
>> Sure absolutely. So in in theus there's
a stipulation that that states if um
revenues um come in above 10% I believe
over the budget then there's a onetime
2.5% lump sum bonus
>> to
>> to employees.
>> Okay. And um is that also in place for
this current fiscal year?
>> The theou is in there. So if we were to
come in over budget of the 10 the 10%
then you would have another payment next
fiscal year.
>> And does your projected uh budget show
us that we would be paying that?
>> It currently does not.
>> You would be under the 10%.
>> We'd be under the 10%.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> But that's an estimate. So you know
what's that? That's an estimate. Yeah.
Understood.
>> And yourus expire June 30, 2026 of this
year. So
>> So this would be the last year
>> potentially
>> depending on what the nextou looks like.
>> Got it.
>> They will have expired before your next
audited financial comes out. So correct.
>> Okay.
>> And it will not be So the way theus are
written currently, they would I I would
think they would still be paid out for
this fiscal year. No. Okay.
>> Um, per the city's financial policies,
unassigned fund balances, and that's
your your savings account that exceed
any policy requirements. So, that's your
available amount to spend, will be
brought forth to the city council for
options of use that meet the strategic
goals that have been established within
the budget process. So, I would imagine
that um during your your budget
workshop, you would probably be
discussing what what to do with some of
these dollars.
Before I move forward, are there any
questions on this
uh long-term fiscal forecast? Um, so
where we stand today, if conditions
remain exactly as they are today, so
we're not looking at any type of future
adjustments, the general fund begins to
experience structural deficits starting
at fiscal year 2033.
Under this scenario, revenues do not
keep pace with growth and inflation
resulting in declining service levels
over time. So you'll notice that as the
expenditures, which is your orange line,
starts to increase over your revenues,
the blue line, then your fund balances
start to decrease. um as they're making
up for that lost cash flow essentially.
>> Are there any questions before I leave
this slide?
>> Council Roy.
>> Yeah. What's that?
>> Go ahead. Yeah.
>> Okay. Um so the general fund um revenues
that you have projected there u what
percentage of that in general is uh
sales tax. So this is this would still
be like um it's the majority. I don't
have the exact percentage of what sales
tax is in here, but we we project a
certain amount of increase and I
actually did a statistical forecasting
for the revenues moving forward. Um and
we had these numbers validated by our
our um financial advisor um UFI who who
>> does that take into account projects
like Target that is not open yet?
>> It does not. So it's only looking at if
we stayed exactly the way we are today.
>> Got it. Okay. Thank you.
Okay, we're going to move on to
wastewater fund. Um, as of December
31st, 2025, wastewater revenues and
sources of funds totaled 5.8 million and
that's a decrease of 3% uh 180,000 from
the same point last year. And expenses
and use of funds totaled 5.6 6 million
which is approximately a decrease of
16.8% or 1.1 million from last year's
midway point and I'll get into that a
little bit in the next slides.
So your wastewater revenue service or um
sewer service charges fees are build by
monthly and the midyear report
represents two billings. Wastewater
revenues are slightly down this year in
comparison to last year and that's um
it's very slight and that's due to lower
investment returns which we already kind
of touched on.
Wastewater expenses are down from
midpoint last year. Um that's mostly due
to reduction needed in the transfer for
uh debt service. Um if you all remember
that there was a wastewater bond
refinancing earlier this fiscal year and
so there wasn't as much needed for that
transfer for the debt service. So that
is that is what contributes to that
reduction.
And your wastewater revenues are
projected to come in at 1.9 million over
budget and expenses are projected to be
1 million below budget u with savings
and personnel and operating costs.
Before I move to transit, are there any
questions
for transit revenues? As of December
31st, 2025, tra trans transit revenues
and sources of funds totaled 1.8
million. That's a decrease of less than
1% 17,000 from the same point last year.
And that's mostly due a delay in the
measure A payment.
Expenses and uses of funds are 1.7
million or 46% at midyear. And this
represents a 21% or 288,000 increase
from the same point last year. um and
that's mostly in personnel. The
following table shows midear
expenditures and organized um
[clears throat and cough]
the same way that we've done all the
other ones um as well as the two
preceding years.
Transit revenues and expenses are
projected to remain within budget and
any funds not spent by year are returned
to RCTC.
Before I move on, are there any
questions?
So for recommended budget adjustments,
uh we do recommend the umou bonus pay
the $67,888.
Uh that would be from the general fund
fund balance reserve. Um general fund
operating is community enhancement is
requesting additional funds for
increased weed abatement and vector
control costs in the amount of $75,337.
uh general fund operating for building
additional funds for several large
development commercial project plan
reviews at 70,000.
Wastewater has requested additional
funds to cover cost of repairs and
protection of city sewer mainline at
$356,197.
the self-insurance fund. There are
settlements and claims from litigation
in the amount of 1,317,253.
Um, and for other funds, we have
professional services agreement for care
coordination services utilizing the
opioid settlement funds of $45,000.
And um, we also have a purchase of a K9
dog with the offset of a donation and
that's in the amount of $20,000.
as well as you have your CIP um budget
adjustments that were discussed earlier
in this meeting are also attached.
So with that, that concludes my report
and I'm available for any questions you
have.
>> All right, thank you for that. Uh
[snorts] Nicole, do we have any public
comment?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time. All
right, then I will open it up for
council further discussion questions.
>> Council member Lara.
>> Yeah, I just have a a couple. Jennifer,
back on uh you have the general fund uh
slide.
Don't know what slide number it is. I
apologize.
>> You looking at revenues or expenditures?
>> Well, I'm looking at revenues and
expenditures. you have u what you do you
listed the 23 24 midyear then you listed
the 2425
the the question is the 2526 midyear
there's a $5 million gap where we have
expenditures over revenues do are we
missing something from the county as far
as my because I know that this is just a
projection and we get money on different
payment cycles but I would kind of hope
that the county would kind of maintain
their payment cycles so that when I look
at midyear your projections like we can
see some type of consistency but this is
a concerning I'm just wondering are we
missing something that they didn't send
us out or
>> we I I went back and look at that and
actually the the payment that we were
missing um that was delayed was uh in
the transit fund. So what this is is
actually those investment returns that
we had discussed earlier but also too
that costs have increased for this
fiscal year. So, a lot of that
difference that you're seeing is that
you have higher costs um and and the
revenue is not increasing at the same
amount as the cost.
>> Okay. So, you but there you're good with
it. You don't see any red flags that we
need to be looking out for as we move
>> because the estimates do show that
revenue would come in higher than what's
projected as well as um expenditures
would come in lower.
>> Okay. And then on the status quo, I I
like that you show that. Um, but does
that include current capital improvement
projects,
right? You include all that. So,
obviously status quo doesn't include the
police station because we haven't
budgeted for that yet in future fire
stations or anything like that. So, if
we just stayed the same,
>> right? So, we So, when we budget for
capital projects, those are transfers
out and those go directly to the capital
projects fund, right? So they don't stay
within the general funding count for any
future years. So that does this does not
um incorporate any future projects that
are are on the list because that can be
that's that's council council decision
at the point in time when you have
budget workshops. Right.
>> Um and yeah it's it's just mostly your
operations and if those were to continue
the way they are now.
>> Right. Okay.
>> So no additional staff or or anything
like that.
>> Right. Staffing is going to impact that.
Contracts will impact that. Yeah. So any
ongoing costs that you add from this
point forward would essentially move
that needle forward.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. I appreciate
that.
>> All right. Very good. Okay. Thank you
for that. I think it's just a is it a
receipt file
>> and approve the budget amendments that
are attached.
>> All right. Then I will
make a motion to receive and file and
approve the budget amendments.
>> I'll second. I get a roll call.
>> Council member Laura,
>> yes.
>> Council member Finn,
>> Council member Martinez,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Prom White,
>> Mayor Voy,
>> yes.
>> All right.
>> Thank you.
[clears throat]
>> It was a good one.
>> All right. We will move on to item J8.
Request to approve a second homeless
enforcement officer position. Staff
report by Mr. Lent.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening, Madame Mayor. I'm city
[clears throat] council. Uh I'm before
you this evening requesting approval to
create a second homeless lison officer
position which would be assigned to a
weekend coverage and would allow for
7day a week homeless enforcement
services.
Uh the request is due to an increased
homeless population and regional impacts
that have compounded uh the issue of
homeless in our community.
Neighboring cities and jurisdictions
have recently disable uh disbanded
several large encampments
and increased their enforcement of uh
their homeless. Specifically, one of our
neighboring cities recently added a
second homeless officer themselves and
they've uh increased their enforcement
efforts.
um they're they also went to a seven day
a week enforcement um as well. So uh due
to the proximity of these jurisdictions,
these uh actions have resulted in
displacement of homeless individuals
into our community, specifically our
retail commercial areas. We're seeing
that effect. Uh for this reason uh the
additional uh second homeless lison
officer will assist in immediately
addressing the increase uh in the
homeless population here in the city of
Bulmont. Uh with that um I'm available
for any questions uh that you may have.
>> Righty. Great. Thank you. Um do we have
any public comment for this item?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time.
>> All right. Seeing no public comment,
I'll open it up to council discussion or
a motion. Mayor Promway. Nope. Uh,
Council Member Martinez.
>> Uh, yeah. Thank you, Mayor. Couple of
quick questions. Um, is this something
that's open internally first? If an
officer wants to go to this position,
then they can apply for it. Is that how
that works usually? And then we would
fill their position or
>> Yes. Uh, this would be considered one of
our So, we have our existing homeless
ladies and officers. This would be a
second one. and it would be open to um
our officers. They put in a memorandum
and a request and then we would um take
that from generally our patrol officers
and then backfill this with the
requested position for um and hire hire
a new officer.
>> Okay. And you discussed with um the
interim manager and finance perhaps the
sustainability of the new position going
into future budgets. You'd be able to to
handle that in your budget. I believe
this well this one's on uh the remainder
of this year will be on the salary
savings that we currently have
>> and then the uh remainder um has been
discussed uh as far as sustaining that
throughout for the additional position
in the bud upcoming budgets.
>> Okay. So the I think it's something like
211 or something like that. That would
be something that you've discussed that
we'd be able to Okay. All right. Thank
you,
>> Council Member Fed.
>> Uh yes, thank you, Mayor. Uh Lieutenant,
thanks uh thank you for the report. I
appreciate that showing the number of
difference of what has transpired from
2024 to 2025 and certainly helps us to
understand the need there. I do have a
question with the 25 numbers in that um
is it possible an individual could have
been listed more than once on that list?
For example, could they have see mental
health facility at one point? Were they
arrested prior to that? you know, um,
this looks like there's an awful lot of
homeless in Bulmont and I know that's we
we we manage it well and we typically
don't have that many, but I just want to
get your perspective on that. Um, that
is there a possibility that one
individual for per se could be listed in
multiple categories there?
>> Yes, there could be there could be
multiple um contacts. We try to
differentiate on what is a new contact
and what is existing but that's not
necessarily uh split up on those numbers
when it comes to the um additional
breakdown. It could be duplicate as you
said. Yes.
>> Okay. But we are seeing more individual
contacts as a whole. Correct.
>> Correct.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> All righty. I too appreciate the the
data that you guys were able to find
here to to prove that uh increase as
well. I think it's important that as we
continue to ask for employees and other
support that we can provide the data and
the background on why they're needed. So
I really appreciate that um and the
effort that went into that. Um with that
I will entertain a motion.
Mayor, I I move that we approve the
addition of one police [snorts] officer
position to the police department's
fiscal year 2526 budget and approve the
necessary budget adjustment of $70,000
to the personnel budget to fund the
position for the remainder of the
current fiscal year.
>> I'll second.
>> Can I get a roll call, please?
>> Council member Laura,
>> yes.
>> Council member Finn,
>> Council member Martinez,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Prom White,
>> Mayor Vo,
>> yes.
>> All right. Thank you for continuing to
keep our city safe. All right, we will
move to um our last action item, J9,
city council meeting dates for 2026. And
um Miss Wheelright, can we get a report
from you? Good evening, council. This
item is for review um of the 2026 city
council meeting dates. Um, this is to
help determine if any meeting dates need
to be considered for cancellation based
on conflicting schedules or upcoming
holidays. This helps staff plan um for
staff reports and meet deadlines. So, in
your staff report is a list of all of
the city council meeting dates. I've
bolded the ones that have potential
conflicts and ones that have been
cancelled previously during the summer
months for your review. And I'm happy to
answer any questions.
>> All right. Thank you. Do we have any
public comments on this item?
>> I have no written requests. Simone, do
we have any callers on the line?
>> We have no callers at this time. All
>> righty. Thank you. Uh I will kind of
start us off. Um we wanted to bring this
forward um for council discussion as I
um think that we have some opportunity
to continue to move things forward. um
the conflict with Washington DC. Uh
there will still be a quorum on the 21st
uh with three council members. Um and my
suggestion would be that we continue
that meeting. Um and we assign somebody
uh to run the meeting as the mayor proim
and myself will be in Washington DC. Um
but I do think that we can continue if
we have a quorum. Uh and if anything
needed to be continued uh we could
continue that meeting if we if we needed
to. Um,
ICSC, I think we had previously uh
talked about that. I believe there are
two of us going to that event again. Uh,
the same two that will be attending DC.
We could continue to leave that on as
well if we wanted to, unless there were
more council members that were planning
on attending ICS, which uh, you know,
are are good to go with. Um,
historically, we have canled the July
7th one. Uh, I personally have no
oppositions to keeping that one uh,
dark. I would prefer to keep August 4th
moving forward and not be dark uh so
that we can continue with business. And
uh I think we've all agreed in the past
that election day, especially with three
council members uh is difficult. So I
would suggest that we go dark on on that
um on that meeting. So essentially I
would be replacing August 4th as a
canceled meeting uh with November 3rd.
Uh, and so looking at this, my
suggestion is that we
um only cancel or only go dark on July
7th and November 3rd.
>> Mayor, if I could interject. So on the
the top of the next page on the agenda
shows January 25th. I'm sure it was a
typo um because it says 2026. It should
be 2027.
>> Oh, sorry. I did not. So, I think that
is far enough into the new year away
from the holiday that perhaps we we keep
that meeting on the schedule. Also,
>> I'm good with that.
[snorts]
>> Any other input, Council Member or Mayor
Pro Tim White?
>> No, I I agree. I think the uh the uh
list here makes sense. I had a feeling
last year that we um or
2025 we were um we were sort of loading
up on on a number of meetings that we um
should try and avoid that so that we
don't have the long meetings and we can
also um better time the the issue. So I
agree with the suggestions that have
been made so far.
>> Member Laura, any objections or
discussion from you? Just a
just question on uh April 21st. Um
there's no way to relo that meeting to
Washington on the one in Washington. You
have to be it has to be that week.
>> So we have an item that we'll be
discussing on the city manager report
which is our budget workshop. Uh we as
as I discussed this with uh city staff
earlier um the proposal was for April
28th to be that budget meeting
>> um for our budget workshop if we would
like to consider another date. Um I'm
okay with that. It depends on everybody
else. Um but my thoughts were you could
continue with the
>> Wouldn't that have to be a special
meeting if it's not on our regular
schedule?
Yes, I
>> I'm not talking about moving the our
meeting. Our meeting could be held. I'm
just didn't know if there was a way to
move the Washington DC meeting.
>> Oh, I see what you're saying.
>> If I may, uh, mayor and council, so
initially April 20th was what was
brought out and then we talked about uh
moving the Washington trip to the next
week. However,
>> uh there were going to be problems with
Congressman Ruiz being available and so
we went back to the 20th. Um, however,
since then, uh, council member Fen has
indicated he will not be attending. So,
there's only the mayor and the mayor PM
attending. Therefore, the idea was to
keep April 21st open and not cancel
April 21st.
>> Okay. Do will we know do we know that um
this temporary partial shutdown is going
to still make it beneficial for us to be
in Washington?
We we had a call with Jamie Jones
yesterday and uh we're we're good to go
for the 20th
>> then. Yeah, we can keep that council
meeting and then one on May 19th as well
as long as we have a
enough staff or enough council members.
So
>> So if I can clarify what I'm hearing is
cancel July 7th and November 3rd only
and everything else stays open, stays
on,
>> I think so. Yeah,
>> that's as I hear it.
>> I think
All right,
we have enough direction. We're good.
Okay, very good. Then we will move on to
K1, our legislative update.
We will have Miss Navvice.
>> Good evening, Mayor and Council.
[laughter]
This item provides um a brief
legislative update on Senate bills from
the 202526
session that staff is currently
monitoring for potential impacts to the
city. The state legislature reconvened
in January and activity has picked up as
bills moving through committees. At this
point, many bills are still being
amended. So staff's focus is on tracking
potential impacts and keeping council
informed as things continue to develop.
One important timing note for the
council's awareness is that February the
20th is the final day for bills to be
introduced this legislative year. So
because of that, we expect to see
additional bills uh introduced or
amended over the next couple of days and
staff will continue to monitor and
report back on those as needed. Now, a
few highlights from the bills included
in the staff report include AB35,
which would speed up how Proposition 4
bond funding guidelines are developed.
This could help uh accelerate timelines
for infrastructure, water, and climate
related grant programs.
AB1421
directs the state to study mileagebased
road usage fees. While this is only a
study, it could have long-term
implications for transportation funding
and for future compliance requirements.
There are also several housing and
transit oriented development bills,
including SB 677, SB722,
and SB908,
which may affect development standards,
densities, and local land use authority
depending on their final form.
SB423, which is expected to be
reintroduced, could eliminate local real
property transfer taxes, which may
affect local revenue if enacted.
SB77 is cleanup legislation which is
anticipated to clarify Brown Act
language access and teleconferencing
requirements adopted last year.
I want to also briefly flag two last
minute bills that were not included in
the written report but are now being
tracked by staff as well. And this
includes AB1439
which relates to public retirement
systems and would require CalPERS and
Calsters to report on how labor
standards affect investments. While
largelyformational,
it could influence future discussions
related to public workforce and
retirement policy.
AB 1383 affects public retirement
systems for safety members and city
staff is monitoring it due to the
potential impacts on retirement benefits
or system requirements for public safety
agencies.
Overall, staff will continue tracking
these bills and evaluating their
potential fiscal and operational impacts
um and will return to council if policy
or direction or advocacy is needed.
Tonight's recommended action is simply
to receive and file the legislative
update. And I'm available if you have
any questions.
>> All right. Great. Thank you. Council
member Finn, do you have a question?
>> Yeah, just a quick comment, Britney. We
I really appreciate the format of this
and having the description of the bill
and the link and so forth. It's nice and
user friendly. So, I appreciate that
because as we write down numbers and so
forth, it's it's so easy to get lost in
the number of the bill, but to have it
right there is is great. So, appreciate
it. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> And Mayor Promoy,
>> uh, nothing.
>> All right. Well, very good. We will
receive and file this report and thank
you for the hard work in getting all
this together. We do appreciate the
format. Uh, as discussed earlier, it's
nice to be able to reference it when we
need to.
>> Excellent. Thank you. All right, we will
move on to economic development update.
>> Uh, we do not have an update this
evening.
>> All right. And I don't believe we have a
planning commission update as they did
not meet.
>> That's correct. Okay. City treasurer,
>> no update.
>> All right. City clerk.
>> All right. City attorney.
>> Nothing.
>> All right. So, that will move us to our
city manager report.
>> Yes, we have the January city manager
monthly report for your review. And
also, uh, we'd like to set the date and
time for the budget workshop. Staff is
recommending Tuesday, April 28th. That's
um wouldn't be um continued meeting.
We're talking about just a separate
meeting from the 7th and the 21st.
So, I'd like to ask uh the mayor and the
council if you would be okay with that
meeting or if you'd propose a different
time and date.
>> We will check our calendars really
quick. That date works for me.
>> What What time are you looking at?
>> We were thinking five o'clock.
>> Okay, that's fine for me.
>> Oh, not time.
>> No, not not nap time. Noon works for me,
but [laughter]
>> you know, just so that we could enjoy
the the festivities all day long, right?
[laughter]
>> 5:00 works for me.
>> You're good, council. All right.
>> I'm good, too.
>> 5:00 PM April 28th. We will miss you,
>> but I know we're in good hands.
>> All right. Do we have What' you say?
>> I said
>> he told me to bring a blanket.
>> Oh, well, we
>> All right. Do we have it is your
favorite sub all of our favorite subject
isn't it? Um do we have any future
agenda items?
>> Um mayor I have one.
>> Yes.
>> Um so as part of our pastcom meetings
that I attend um the question was
brought up is is what was what is the
city's emergency plan? And so if we can
get a just a general review as to how we
work with the state, the county, what
what do we do within the city? How do we
communicate with the HOAs? Um Excuse me.
>> It there was talk there that and I don't
know if this is correct or not, but it
just I'll share this and it might help
staff understand that I think the fire
[clears throat]
perhaps through the fire department or
Cal Fire that um the city's required to
do an update. Maybe the last one was in
2021 or 2022 or something like that. So
how often are those updates? What is
involved from the city? So just kind of
as a general update maybe as a receive
and file report and then we can share
that information with our passcom and
and as a update on passcom it's a sanger
pass area emergency preparedness group
um and we have other individuals that
come in for everybody from um
oh now I'm brain lock um HOAs with their
emergency preparedness um um um
certification um oh what do they call um
>> Calert class, you know, CERT classes and
so forth and even um
>> what's the organization that comes and
helps out when there's a disaster?
>> FEMA.
>> Thank you. Um and um Red Cross, you
know, so Red Cross is there and so
forth. So,
>> wow.
>> So, anyway, there's a a big group of
folks that come together and and and we
all want to just have it some better
direction so we can better work as a as
an information committee in a sense. Um,
and so we we feel like we're just we're
losing a little bit of focus and that
we're just getting individual updates of
what's going on with each organization
versus, hey, well, what's the do we have
a general plan? Do we have a regional
plan? That sort of thing. So, I don't
want to get too far into the weed, but
something to to to for us to better
understand and share with with that
group.
>> That's all. All right. That's all I have
on that one.
>> All right. Excellent. And Mayor Promay.
>> Um, yeah, I have a couple. I don't know
why, but in the last week I've had a
number of people come up to me and ask
me about why we don't have bike racks at
all of our businesses.
Um, and so I think they made some good
points. Uh, they were a little
dumbfounded when I asked them, "You mean
all our businesses?" And they said,
"Yes." And and then I asked them, "Um,
even a mattress store?" And they were,
[laughter] "Well, maybe not that." So
I I think we should we should consider
that whether or not that becomes part of
a planning process or not. Um and then
the other thing um
I think we need to have
aformational
and discussion on our water master. Um,
you know, I've got some concerns there
with the way it is made up and the
controlling um
the controlling legislation or judgment
um that was originally written by the
three of our former uh department heads
who've all been convicted of felonies.
Um, and I I really believe we're at a
disadvantage, the city of Bumont,
because there's some other folks
representing the other agencies that um
are acting on um without the kind of
accountability that I believe they
should be having. And that was why my
discussion my questions earlier was what
role the water master and Ukipa Valley
water district has because if we get to
the point where we're going to have to
have that kind of um discussion about
mitigating the water going down. I just
I just want to revisit where we stand. I
I don't think a lot of us even know what
the water master is made up of and what
what the controlling document is on
that. But um I think it's important that
we consider that for a future agenda
item.
Okay.
All right. And anyone else?
All right. We will put those down.
All right. Can I get um Council Member
Fen for your council reports?
>> Certainly. Thank you, Mayor. Um I've got
a few meetings I attended in the last
two weeks. Um on the 4th, I attended the
city's community visiting workshops. I
appreciate the economic development team
for putting that together. Um, also that
same day I was given the opportunity to
give a property tax presentation to
Birkshshire Hathaway's real estate
office here in town. [clears throat] And
so I so I continue to show off our
little CFD search tool there and help
them out. So that was that was
beneficial. Um, also attended that same
day um, Riverside Transits Finance
Committee meeting. Uh, the following day
after that on the 5th um, I attended our
T our local T now. That's the
transportation now um committee. And
then on the 5th um we had a veterans
expo recap. Um and what the ex the the
group was doing in the past is we were
having a large veterans expo in January
um tied in with a job fair and then
another smaller event in August. And so
I proposed and the group agreed to drop
the August,
focus on a yearly event and then make it
an expo only. The job fair was adding a
layer of difficulty, you know, to that
some disruption as well. Um, some of us
experienced that. We've gotten better as
we were, you know, as as years gone on.
But I propose that with then we leave
that with staff and our economic
development department. They are the
experts. let them put that on with the
little plug, hey, hire a veteran when
you can, you know. And so, um, I pass
that information on to our city manager
and to, um, our economic development
director as a suggestion. Um, and so I
think going forward that will be more
productive and and we'll leave that to
the experts. And then um final two
meetings, Cal City's regional meeting
and then also I had the opportunity to
um participate with the Bowmont Police
Department for our drone demo and I am
super excited about that. So um so
that's my report for the evening. Thank
you, mayor.
>> Yes, thank you. Maybe include uh county
workforce development. I'm sure staff
will take that up for that job fair as
well. All right, Council Member Lara.
>> Uh thank you, Mayor. Uh February 4th, I
attended the Bulmont Unified School
District CTE showcase, which is uh
amazing. I appreciate Laura and Joe for
going out and attending that to support
that. Um I can remember back in the day
when it was just wood shop and auto
shop. Uh now there's uh 12 different
>> awesome
>> vocational paths to take, which is
excellent. Um February 11th, Coffee with
a Cop was well attended. Was great as
always. uh 12th. Yeah, the the drone
demo was was definitely amazing. Um
looking forward to having that come back
to council.
Um and then finally, I just want to know
um one of the things I I like to ask a
lot of frequently on the heavy rains,
how how did the wastewater This is
critical to me because failure to
maintain our wastewater ends up could
cost us the city money. So, um, our
plant
>> No, I I actually appreciate you
answering. It gives me opportunity to
recognize our staff. Um, yeah, we did
experience really high rain flows. Um,
I've got some graphs here. You can see
it just jumps off the page what happens
when we get those kind of flows. And we
had staff out addressing um, you know,
high flows at both the plant and uh,
throughout the collection system. It
also shows that our monitoring systems
working.
>> Yeah. Um, we have the uh the smart
covers. We had one go off out there by
the golf course, so the crews responded.
>> We had some high wet well levels. Uh,
Noble Creek area got a lot of inflow in
the plant, but um we had no spills. We
had no violations and the plant uh
processed all the extra flow.
>> See, that's what I love to hear. It's uh
this council invested a lot of time and
energy into that and money. And again,
thanks to your staff for monitoring
that. Uh, I know it interrupts uh, it's
late night and interrupts sleep, but I
do appreciate their efforts. Thank you.
That's all I have. Mayor,
>> thank you for highlighting that. Agreed.
I always think about that. Council
member Martinez.
>> Yeah, just very briefly, um, attended
the Cal City's Riverside County Division
meeting uh, at Dwit um, sponsored by
Manning. Uh, the youth council again
continuing to meet. Great um, uh, number
of students are participating. Thank
you, mayor, for attending. they really
um really learned a lot and you can tell
by their faces they were really engaged.
So, thank you for that. Um the economic
development uh city visioning workshop,
I attended that last one via Zoom and
the PD drone demo. Um I'm really looking
forward to that discussion when it
comes. Thank you.
>> All right. Thank you, Mayor Pro.
>> Um so, Robert, what is the P phase and
transportation?
>> Okay, turned off.
a project initiation document.
>> Okay. So, that was approved by RCTC for
the Bowmont 79 interchange
>> about uh 1.2 million to 1.3 million and
it's all funded by TUM at this point and
that's all I have to report.
>> Well, that's good news for another large
area for the city. All right. I was
fairly busy the last uh couple two
weeks. So, uh, February 4th, we had the,
uh, collaboration committee. Um, the
Sanonio Pass Water Agency is now hosting
that. Uh, so we appreciate them for
hosting us and always a great, um,
meeting. Council member Fen, the focus
for this meeting, they want to talk
about um, emergency and have an
emergency focus. So I think part of the
conversation and and maybe that um
presentation that you asked for we can
take to that uh team as well. On the 5th
uh I had the opportunity and pleasure to
speak with the um the Rotary Club here
in Bumont. Uh very engaged. It was
awesome to be there with everybody. Uh I
was able to show off our CIP. Well, not
really show off but direct them to our
CIP.
um
I don't want to call it a workflow, but
I guess project status uh I'll say for
that and they had some excellent um
questions. I really appreciate all staff
that came for that. Also, I attended the
economic development on 26 Calvary
Christian uh came and met us here uh to
learn about what we do here at city
council. They also were very engaging.
29 we were at the Cal's dinner. 211 uh
was a four seasons meeting. I really
want to thank um assistant or excuse me
our uh interim city manager. Uh you
spoke very eloquently to that um group
of people and I really appreciate the
engagement and all the efforts uh that
went forth from the city along with um
our fire chief uh Chief Hopkins did an
excellent job as well um talking about
fire mitigation in a concerned area for
four seasons. So, I really appreciate
all the work that went in to that and
the collaboration that's going into that
with uh the developer along with um the
agency that's going to help mitigate
212. I am happy to report that we
dismantled Erica in a record meeting
time of like 4 minutes, I think. So, uh
of course it was on a day that I was not
in the desert already and had to drive
to the desert for that 4-minute meeting,
but it's all good. We have um we have
finished our obligations there and all
cities have signed to move over to the
PAC and they will be reimbursing
whatever is left um amongst the cities.
So
>> how many years was Erica in place
>> 2008 it started in 2008.
>> Yes. So that I can we can officially
check that off and whoever is the next
mayor does not need to sign an Erica
represent.
>> I do have to bring I do have to bring
the resolution back to this board for
you all to sign up. city now has to go
back to cities.
>> I hate to interrupt you, but I do want
to let um let those on council know who
may not have known,
>> but it was because of the relationship
of the uh city of the attorney for Erica
that led us to our city attorney.
>> Oh, excellent.
>> that many years ago. So,
>> so we can thank that.
>> We can we can thank that. Uh
>> there's a lot of collaboration that came
out of that. And then I too attended the
drones. Uh I think that that is uh I'm
looking forward to that coming back. So
with that, I will continue
um this meeting uh this clo our for
close session to Monday the 23rd at
1700. Um and we will adjourn for now and
reconvene on Monday.
>> At what time? Monday.
>> I said 1700. 5 p.m.
>> Sorry,
>> I wrote 1700 down so I just read it.
5:00 p.m.
I don't know if I should do that.